“…1997年将有五十亿人口 死于致命病毒
幸存者将会离开地球表面
世界将再度由动物统治…”
节录自一段访谈 受访对象经临床诊断患有精神分裂
1990年4月12号- 巴尔的摩郡立医院
Flight 784 for San Francisco is now ready for boarding.
搭乘841航班前往罗马的旅客 请到七号登机口
Passengers for flight 841 to Rome, come to gate seven.
搭乘784航班前往旧金山的旅客 现在开始登机…
Flight 784 to San Francisco is now ready for boarding at...
病患代号87645，詹姆斯柯尔
Inmate number 87645: Cole, James.
27631，强森
27631: Johnson.
84743，伊尼斯
84743: Innis.
荷西
Jose. Psst.
- 荷西，怎么回事？ - 坏消息
Jose, what's going on? -  Bad news, man.
- 又要征志愿者？ - 对，而且你被点名了
Volunteers? -  Yeah. And they said your name.
或许他们会给你特赦哦
Hey, maybe they'll give you a pardon, man.
是哦，所以才没有志愿者回来 他们全都被特赦了
Yeah. That's why none of the volunteers... come back. They all get a pardon.
- 我听说有人回来啊 - 对啦
Some come back, I heard. -  Yeah.
放我回去！ 别选我
Please put me back. Don't take me.
他们把人送到七楼藏起来
Yeah, they got 'em up on the... seventh floor. They hide 'em up there.
他们头脑全都有问题，神智异常
They're all messed up in the head. Brains don't work.
你哪知道他们是不是头脑有问题 又没人看过他们
You don't know they're all messed up.
或许不是头脑有问题 那是谣言，没人知道真假
Nobody's seen 'em. And maybe they're not messed up. That's a rumor. Nobody knows that.
我不信
I don't believe that.
祝你好运
Good luck, man.
志愿义务
Volunteer duty.
我没自愿
-  I didn't volunteer.
你又想惹麻烦？
You causing trouble again?
不，没有
No, no trouble.
以下是给新人的指示
These are the instructions for the first time probe.
请专心聆听并恪遵无误
Listen carefully. They must be followed exactly.
衣服上的所有开口都必须完全封闭
All openings of your garment must be sealed completely.
连身衣若有任何破损
If the integrity of the suit is compromised in any way,
布料被扯破或拉链没拉好
if the fabric is torn or a zipper not closed,
将被拒绝归返
readmittance will be denied.
我们做到了
若有染菌情形
If there are any... indications of contamination by germs,
将拒绝该名人员归返 以保他人安全
the subject will be denied reentry to secure population.
请将血液样本放入容器内
Please place... blood sample in receptacle provided.
根据永久紧急令第六条
There will be a socialization class in room 700...
700室将开设社交课程
for citizens cited for deviations 23- A and 96- A...
嘉惠23- A及96- A行为偏差之公民
per subchapter six... of the Permanent Emergency Code.
詹姆斯柯尔未遭感染
James Cole cleared from quarantine.
谢谢，你们两个到外面等
Thank you. You two wait outside.
博士，他有暴力前科
He's got a history, Doctor. Violence.
反社会指数6，不断违背永久紧急令
Antisocial six.
科学家说：“治疗已经太迟”
Repeated violations of the Permanent Emergency Code.
傲慢、藐视
Insolence. Defiance.
百万人恐惧末日即将来临
Disregard of authority.
漠视权威，徒刑25年到终生监禁
Doing 25 to life.
我想他不会伤害我们
I don't think he's gonna hurt us.
柯尔先生，你不会伤害我们吧？
You aren't gonna hurt us, are you, Mr. Cole?
不，长官
No, sir.
柯尔先生，请坐
Why don't you sit down, Mr. Cole?
我们很感激你自愿 你是很优秀的观察员
We appreciate your volunteering. You're a very good observer.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们有项先进的计划，有别于以往
We have a very advanced program. Something very different.
让你灭刑的良机
Opportunity to reduce your sentence.
在将人类带回地表一事上
And possibly play an important role...
你或许能扮演重要角色
in returning the human race to the surface of the Earth.
我们需要意志坚强、有毅力的人
We want tough- minded people. Strong mentally.
之前用意志力薄弱的人 都没有好下场
We've had some misfortunes with... unstable types.
以你的状况来说，这是大好机会
For a man in your position, an opportunity.
不志愿才是大错
Not to volunteer could be a real mistake.
绝对是大错
Definitely a mistake.
“在大量的微波
'Yet among the myriad microwaves,
“红外线讯息以及 以十亿位组计的电脑讯息中
the infrared messages, the gigabytes of ones and zeros,
“我们发现了文字 现在才位元大小
we find words, byte- sized now,
巴尔的摩- 1990年4月
`“甚至比科学还微小 在混沌的电子中忽隐忽现
tinier even than science, lurking in some vague electricity.
“但我们只要聆听
But if we but listen,
“就会听到那位诗人寂寞的声音在说
we hear the solitary voice of that poet telling us...
“昨日之狂已备下
yesterday this day's madness did prepare...
“明日之沉默胜利或绝望
tomorrow's silent triumph of despair.
“喝吧，因为你不知道 为何而来、又来自何方
Drink, for you know not whence you came, nor why.
“喝吧，因为你不知道 为何而去、又去向何处”
Drink, for you know not why you go, nor where.'
…漫游在他的底裤
...wandering around in nothing but his underpants...
与透明的塑胶女性雨衣之间
and one of those plastic, see- through lady's raincoats.
然后他们过去，好声好气地 请那人出示身分
So, they get there, they ask the guy real nice for some kind of I.D.
他生气了，开始大叫说有病毒
He gets agitated, starts screaming about viruses.
完全不理智、没有判断力
Totally irrational, totally disoriented.
不知道自己在哪 也不知道今天星期几
Doesn't know where he is, what day of the week it is.
我看看
Lemme see.
- 他们只搞清楚他的名字 - 谢了
All they got was his name. -  Thanks.
当然，他们猜他是嗑了药
Of course, they figured he's stoned out of...
某种精神病患之类的
his mind. Some kind of psychotic episode.
- 做过药性检测了？ - 结果是阴性
He's been tested for drugs? -  Negative for drugs.
但他打倒了五名警察 像是被下了很重的药
But he took on five cops like he was dusted to the eyeballs.
- 结果却没有，你信吗？ - 他被绑起来了
No drugs. You believe that? -  He's in restraints.
对啊，你没在听吗？ 有两名警察受伤住院了耶！
Yeah. Weren't you listenin'? I've got... two police officers in the hospital.
医生替他打了大量乐利静 你看他，还精神百倍的
The medic gave him enough stellazine to... kill a horse. Look at him. Rarin' to go.
那就能解释身上的瘀青了，他挣扎过
That would explain the bruises, I guess. The struggle.
对，你要进去检查吗？
Yeah. You wanna go in there, examine him, what?
要
Yes, please.
就只有这样？ 查过系统资料了吗？
Is this all you have? Ran it through your system?
没有结果符合，没有执照 没有指纹也没有拘捕令，什么都没
No matchup. No license, no prints, no warrants. Nothing.
我看我跟你一起进去好了
I should probably go in with you. -  No, thank you.
不，谢了，没那个必要
That won't be necessary. -  All right.
好吧，为防万一，他就在这里
He'll be right here... just in case.
柯尔先生，我叫凯瑟琳瑞利 我是精神科医生
Mr. Cole, my name is Kathryn Railly. I'm a psychiatrist.
我替本郡工作，不是警方的人
I work for the county. I don't work for the police.
因此我只关心你的健康 你懂吗？
So my concern is for your well- being. Do you understand that?
要走！ 要走！
Need to go. Need to go.
我不能叫警察放你走
I can't make the police let you go.
但我很想帮你，所以…
But I do wanna help you, so I...
我需要你告诉我 今晚究竟发生了什么事
I need you to tell me exactly what happened tonight.
詹姆斯，你想你做得到吗？
Do you think you can do that, James?
我能不能叫你詹姆斯？
May I call you James?
詹姆斯
James.
从来没人那样叫过我
Nobody ever calls me that.
- 你是郡立医院的病患吗？ - 不是
Have you been a patient at County? No.
- 我是不是在哪里见过你？ - 不可能
Have I seen you someplace? -  Not possible.
我要走，我要… 我应该要搜集情报的
I need to go. I need to... I'm... supposed to be gathering information.
- 什么情报？ - 说了也没用
What kind of information? -  Won't help you.
对谁都没用，什么也改变不了
Won't help anyone. Won't change anything.
詹姆斯，你知道你为什么在这里吗？
James, do you know why you're here?
因为我是优秀观察员，意志坚决
'Cause I'm a good observer. Got a tough mind.
我懂了
I see.
你不记得曾袭击过警察？
You don't remember assaulting a police officer?
为什么拴住我？ 为什么会有这些链子拴住我？
Why am I chained? Why are these chains on me?
你以前在精神病院里待过，对吧？
You've been in an institution before, haven't you?
- 或者在医院？ - 不！ 我现在就得走！
Or hospital? -  No. Now I need to go.
要走！
Need to go.
- 詹姆斯，你有没有坐过牢？ - 地下的
Have you been in prison, James? -  Underground.
躲避追捕？
Hiding?
我好爱这空气
I love this air.
噢，好美妙的空气
Oh, it's such wonderful air.
- 空气哪里美妙呢？ - 好新鲜，没有细菌
What's wonderful about the air, James? Very fresh. No germs.
你怎么会认为空气中没有细菌呢？
Why do you think there aren't any germs in the air?
- 现在是十月吧？ - 四月
This is October, right? -  April.
- 现在是几年？ - 你以为现在是几年？
What year is this? -  What year do you think it is?
1996.
那是未来，你以为自己活在未来吗？
That's the future, James. Do you think you're living in the future?
- 1996年是过去 - 不，1996年是未来
1996 is the past. No, 1996 is the future.
现在是1990年
This is 1990.
小姐，闭嘴
Shut up, ladies.
你们要带我去哪？
-  Where're you taking me?
法国南部的时髦旅馆 你会喜欢的
South of France, buddy. Fancy hotel. You'll love it.
我不能去，我得打电话
I can't go. I just need to make a telephone call.
对啦，你少说两句吧 你骗得了心理医生可骗不了我们
Yeah, yeah. Zip it, daisy. You fooled...
中士柜开放时间- 6PM到7AM
the shrink, but you don't fool us.
走吧，大哥
Let's go, ace.
好，过来
All right. Come on, come on.
对啦，现在让我看看你的头
There you go. Now, lemme see your head, Jimbo.
- 看看你有没有头虱 - 我要打电话
See if you got any creepy crawlers. -  I need to make a telephone call.
阿詹，得带你去看医生 医生答应了，你才能打电话
Got to take you over to the doctor, Jimbo. Can't make no calls 'til the doctor says.
- 有重要的事！ - 阿詹，你应该放轻松
It's very important. What you gotta do, Jimbo, is take it easy. Relax into things.
轻松下来，我们就能好好相处
And we'll all get along fine if you just relax.
Wow. Whoo- oo.
走吧，快点
Let's go. Come on. Let's go.
嘿，戈恩！
Hey, Goines.
喂，戈恩！
Yo, Goines.
杰佛瑞！
Yo, Jeffrey. Goines.
- 戈恩！ - 干嘛？
What? -  Look here.
看这里，这是詹姆斯
This here's James. Now, do me a favor.
帮我个忙，带他到处看看吧
Why don't you show him around?
把看电视规则告诉他 带他看游戏室之类的，好吗？
Tell him the TV rules. Show him the games and stuff. Okay?
你要给我多少？ 多少？ 因为我等于在帮你工作
How much you gonna pay me? How much? I'd be doin' your job.
五千元，伙伴，够了吗？
Five thousand dollars, my man. That enough?
五千
Five thousand?
老样子，我会开张支票给你
I'll wire a check to your account as usual.
五千元！ 五千元！
Five thousand dollars. Five thousand dollars.
五千元
Five thousand dollars.
我就给他一趟精神病院豪华之旅
I'll give him the deluxe mental hospital tour.
- 好兄弟！ - 耍宝吧，让他们感觉好些
My man. Kid around, makes 'em feel good. We're pals.
我们是好伙伴，我爱你 你是囚犯，不，你是警卫
I love you. You're the prisoners.
你明白了
No, you're the guards.
好，会很好玩喔
Now you got it. Okay, it's all in good fun. Here's some games here.
这里有一些游戏，这边是… 起来！ 起来！
And there's... Get out. Get out.
他坐在我位子上
He was in my chair.
游戏
Games. Games. Here's some games.
这些是游戏，想要逃出来
Games that wanna get out.
看到没？ 更多游戏 游戏会让你变成植物人
See? More games.
看吧？
Games. They vegetize you. See? Aah.
如果你玩游戏，就等于志愿吃镇静剂
If you play the games, you're voluntarily taking a tranquilizer.
看得出他们给你打了舒缓药物
I guess they gave you some chemical restraints..
药物！
Drugs
他们给你打了什么？ 妥瑞辛？ 好度？ 打了多少？
What'd they give you? Thorazine? Haldol? How much? How much?
研究药物，把剂量搞清楚 这是最基本的
Learn your drugs. Know your dosages. It's elementary.
- 我要打电话 - 打电话？
I need to make a telephone call. -  A telephone call?
那是跟外界通讯耶
That's communication with the outside...
医生有指示，不行
world. Doctor's discretion. No.
如果这些疯子都能打电话
If all of these nuts could just make phone calls,
疯病就会透过电话线传播出去
it could spread insanity oozing through telephone cables,
进入那些可怜又没疯的人耳里 害他们变疯
oozing to the ears of all these poor, sane people, infecting them.
到处都是疯子，疯狂瘟疫
Wackos everywhere. A plague of madness.
小詹，其实呢…
In fact, very few, Jim... Jim, very few...
小詹，我们这边很少人是真疯
of us here are actually mentally ill.
我并不是说你没疯 在我看来你简直疯得无可救药
I'm not saying you're not mentally ill. For all I know, you're... crazy as a...
但这不是你进来的原因
loon. But that's not why you're here.
这不是你进来的原因！ 这不是你进来的原因！
That's not why you're here. That's not why you're here.
你进来是因为整个大环境
You're here because of the system.
有台电视，全都在那里了
There's the television. It's all right there. All right there.
全都在
Look, listen, kneel, pray.
看，听、跪、祈祷，广告！
The commercials.
我们不再有生产力，不再制造
We're not productive anymore. Don't...
全都自动化了，那我们有啥用？ 我们是消费者啊
make things anymore. It's all automated. What are we for then? We're consumers, Jim.
好，买很多东西，你是好公民
Okay, okay. Buy a lot of stuff, you're a good citizen.
但如果你不买很多东西 那你算个啥？
But if you don't buy a lot of stuff, what are you then?
什么？ 你就疯了！
What? You're mentally ill.
我说的是事实
Fact, Jim. Fact.
如果你不买东西 卫生纸啦、新车啦
If you don't buy things: toilet paper, new cars,
电动自慰器啦
electrically- operated sexual devices, stereo...
音响设备有植入脑部的耳机
systems with brain- implanted headphones,
螺丝起子有迷你内建式雷达追踪器
screwdrivers with miniature built- in...
语音启动电脑…
radar devices, voice- activated computers...
放轻松，杰佛瑞，镇定点
Take it easy, Jeffrey. Be calm.
好，对，你很迷人
Right. That's right. You're a very attractive woman.
氧气
Hah.
如果你想看某个电视节目 如All My Children
If you want to watch a particular... television program, like All My Children,
就去找护理长，告诉她
you can go to the charge nurse and tell her...
节目播放日期和时间
the day, the time the show you wanna see is on.
但你必须在节目开始前告诉她
But you have to tell her... before the show is scheduled to be on.
有个人总是要求看已经播过的节目
There was this guy, and he was always... requesting shows that had already played.
对，不对，你必须事先告诉她
Yes. No. You have to tell her before.
他却怎样都搞不懂
He couldn't quite grasp the idea that the...
护理长没办法让昨天回来
charge nurse couldn't make it be yesterday.
她无法倒转时间！ 谢谢你，爱因斯坦
She couldn't turn back time. Thank you, Einstein.
现在呢，他是疯子 小詹，他是大智障
Now he, he was nuts. He was a fruitcake, Jim.
够了，杰佛瑞
Okay, that's it, Jeffrey.
你该打针了
You're gonna get a shot.
我警告你了
I warned you. -  Right. Right, right, right.
好好好，我在解释
I got a little carried away...
本院惯例给小詹听 讲着讲着就激动起来了
explaining the inner workings of the institution to Jim.
Hmm? Hmm?
我其实不是真的来自外太空
I don't really come from outer space.
他是瓦盛顿，不是真的来自外太空
Oh. L.J. Washington. He doesn't really come from outer space.
朋友，别学我说话
Don't mock me, my friend.
别坐我的椅子！
Get outta my chair.
这是精神偏差的症状
It's a condition of mental divergence.
我发现自己在欧戈行星上
I find myself on the planet Ogo.
是知识菁英的一份子
Part of an intellectual elite...
准备征服冥王星上的野蛮部落
preparing to subjugate the barbarian hordes on Pluto.
但就算这是能让我全然信服的真实
But even though this is a totally... convincing reality for me in every way,
欧戈再怎么说也只建构在我脑中
nevertheless, Ogo is actually a construct of my psyche.
我有精神偏差
I am mentally divergent...
因为我在逃离那无以名状的现实
in that I am escaping certain unnamed realities...
它侵害了我在此地的人生
that plague my life here.
当我不再逃离时
When I stop going there,
我的病就好了
I will be well.
朋友，你也有偏差吗？
Are you also divergent, friend?
这里是关疯子的地方
This is a place for crazy people.
我没疯
I'm not crazy.
柯尔先生，我们不用 “疯子”这个词
We don't use that term, 'crazy,' Mr. Cole.
这里的人疯得很！
You've got some real nuts here.
我知道一些你们不知道的事
I know some things that you don't know.
要你们理解会很困难
It's gonna be very difficult for you to understand it.
嘿！
Hey. -  Hey, hey.
嘿，我不会伤害人
I'm not gonna hurt anyone.
好吧
All right.
听我说
Look, have any of you heard...
你们有谁听过十二猴子军？
of the Army of the Twelve Monkeys?
他们画了这个
They, they paint this.
他们在每栋建筑物上都印了这个
They stencil this on the sides of buildings everywhere.
见过吗？
Have you seen this?
- 柯尔先生？ - 有没有见过？
-  Mr. Cole?
你要不要花点时间
Why don't you take your time and try...
从头解释一下？
to explain this from the beginning?
对，现在是1990年
Right, right. It's 1990.
好，这样就合理了 他们还没开始行动呢
Okay, that makes sense. They wouldn't've been active yet.
Um...
1996和1997年死了五十亿人
Five billion people died in 1996 and 1997.
全世界的人几乎都死光了
Almost the entire population of the world.
只有百分之一的人活了下来
Only about one percent of us survived.
而你是来拯救我们的？
Are you going to save us?
我怎么救得了？ 事情已经发生了
How can I save you? This already happened.
我救不了你们，谁也没办法
I can't save you. Nobody can.
我只是想搜集情报
I am simply trying to gather information...
帮助现代的人追溯那病毒的根源
to help the people in the present... trace the path of the virus.
- 柯尔先生，我们不在现代吗？ - 不
We're not in the present now, Mr. Cole?
1990年是过去，这件事已经发生了 我想说的就是…
No. 1990 is the past. This already happened. That's what I'm trying...
柯尔先生？
Mr. Cole? Mr. Cole?
所以你相信1996年是现代了？
You believe 1996 is the present then, is that it?
不！ 1996年也是过去 听我说，我是…
No. 1996 is the past too. Listen to me. What I...
我是…
What I...
我只需要打个电话
What I need to do is make a telephone call.
只要打通电话，我就能把事情搞清楚
I can straighten this out if I make a telephone call.
你想打给谁？ 谁会把事情搞清楚？
Who would you call? Who would straighten everything out?
科学家，他们要知道 他们把我送错时间了
The scientists. They'll want to know... that they sent me to the wrong time.
我可以留言，他们会在现代监听
I can leave a voice mail message that they monitor from the present.
拜托，能不能让我打个电话？
Can I just make one telephone call, please?
拜托
Please?
你在狗碗里干嘛？ 给我出来！
What are you doin' in the dog bowl?
谁把多力多滋放进去的？
Get outta there. Who put those Doritos in there anyway?
什么？ 留言？
Yes? What? Voice mail?
我不知道…别吵啦！
Look, I don't know... Stop makin' that noise.
我不知道你在说什么
I don't know what you're talkin' about.
你在开玩笑吗？ 我不认识什么科学家
Is this a joke? I don't know any scientists.
多安，出来…詹姆斯什么？
Duanne, get out... James who?
跟你期待的不一样？
Wasn't who you expected?
不，是个女的，她什么也不知道
No. It was some lady. She didn't know anything.
或许你打错了
Well, maybe it was the wrong number.
不，我就是因为记性好 他们才选我的
No. That's why they chose me. I remember things.
詹姆斯，你在哪里长大的？
James, where did you grow up?
瑞利医生
Dr. Railly.
我有种很怪的感觉 好像以前见过你
I have the strangest feeling I've met you before.
等等，现在是1990年
Wait. This is 1990. I'm supposed to be...
我应该在1996年留话的！
leaving messages in 1996.
那个电话还不对！ 问题就在这里！
It's not the right number yet. That's the problem.
我们有个讯息给他们
We have a message for them.
不！
No.
不行啦，你打不开的
Won't work. Can't open it.
你以为可以移开铁网 其实不行，已经被焊死了
You think you can remove the grill, but you can't. It's welded.
看吧？ 早说过了，每扇门也都锁住了
See? Told you. All the doors are locked too.
他们要保护外面的人 不受我们伤害
They're protecting the people on the outside from us...
可是外面的人就跟我们一样疯狂
when the people on the outside are as crazy as us.
你知道“疯狂” 是啥？ 疯狂就是少数服从多数，对！
Do you know what 'crazy' is? Crazy is majority rules. Yeah.
就拿细菌来说吧
Take germs for example.
细菌？
Germs? -  Uh- huh.
十八世纪还没有这种东西
In the eighteenth century, no such thing. Nada. Nothing.
没有，也没人想得出这种东西！
No one ever imagined such a thing.
至少神经正常的人想不出来
No sane person anyway.
然后有一位医生…
Along comes this doctor. Uh, uh...
塞麦尔维斯！
Semmelweis. Semmelweis.
塞麦尔维斯出现，想要说服大家
Semmelweis comes along and he's trying...
主要是其他医生
to convince people, other doctors mainly,
有种很小很小、看不见的坏东西 名叫细菌
that there are these teeny, tiny, invisible bad things called germs...
会钻进人的身体，让人生病
that get into your body and make you sick.
他想叫医生去洗手
He's trying to get doctors to wash their hands.
这人怎么样？疯了吗？
What is this guy? Crazy?
很小很小，看不见的 “你说啥？ 细菌？什么？ ”
Teeny, tiny, invisible 'what do you call 'em? Germs? Huh? What?'
现在切换到二十世纪
Now, cut to the twentieth century.
准确来说是上周 就在我被拖进这间肮脏病房之前
Last week as a matter of fact, right... before I got dragged into this hellhole.
我到速食店点了一份汉堡
I go in to order a burger in this fast- food...
那人把汉堡掉在地上
joint. The guy drops it on the floor.
小詹，他捡起来，拍一拍 像没事一样要递给我
Jim, he picks it up, wipes it off. He hands it to me like it was all okay.
“有细菌耶！ ”我说 他说：“我不信有细菌
'What about the germs?' I say. He says, 'I don't believe in germs.
“细菌是人家掰出来
Germs are a plot they made up so they...
“好让你去买消毒剂和肥皂的”
can sell you disinfectants and soaps.'
他疯了，对吧？ 看吧？
Now, he's crazy, right? See?
没有对，没有错，只有受欢迎的意见
There's no right. There's no wrong. There's only popular opinion.
你！ 你相信有细菌吧？
You, you, you believe in germs, right?
我没疯
I'm not crazy.
当然没疯！ 你想逃出去吧？ 这很正常
Of course not. You wanna escape, right? That's very sane.
我可以帮你，你要我帮忙对吧？ 帮你逃出去？
I can help you. You want me to, don't ya? Get you out?
你知道怎么逃出去？
You know how to get outta here?
- 没错，小子！ - 那你怎么不逃？
Yes, my son. Then why don't ya?
我为什么不逃？ 你准备这么问
Why don't I try to escape? That's what you were gonna ask.
好问题，非常好的问题，很聪明
Good question. Very good question. Intelligent.
因为我疯了才会想逃 我已经传出消息了
Because I would be crazy to escape. I have sent out word.
我的情况在掌握中
I am all taken care of.
什么意思？
-  What does that mean?
我已经设法连络到几位手下、恶灵
I've managed to contact certain underlings, evil spirits,
秘书的秘书和其他各种爪牙们
secretaries of secretaries, and other...
他们会联系我父亲
assorted minions who will contact my father.
等我父亲知道我在这种地方
And when my father finds out I'm in this kind of place,
就会叫他们 把我转到一流的精神病院去
he'll have them transfer me to one of those classy joints...
那里的人会把你当个人看 像待客那样好好招待你
where they treat you properly, like a person, a guest.
像大饭店那样有床单、浴巾
With sheets and towels like a big hotel,
还有给疯子、狂人、颠邪者吃的好药
with great drugs for all of us nut- case, lunatic, maniac devils.
抱歉
Sorry. Uh, sorry.
我有些激动
I got a little agitated.
又兴起了逃走的念头，突然就…
The thought of escape crossed my mind. And suddenly...
突然就想把铁柱扳回去！
Suddenly I felt like bending the fucking bars back.
拆掉该死的窗栏，再把它们吃掉！
And ripping out the goddamn window...
对，吃掉！
frames and eating them. Yes, eating them.
然后跳、跳、跳！
And leaping, leaping, leaping.
大家来灌肠唷！
Colonics for everyone.
好啦！ 蠢蛋，我是精神病患耶
Ahh, all right. You dumb assholes, I'm a mental patient.
本来就该行为狂悖啊
I'm supposed to act out.
有一天你们这些智障会知道我是谁！ 我父亲会很不爽喔
Wait'll you morons find out who I am. My father's gonna be really upset.
我父亲不爽起来，大地都会震动
And when my father gets upset, the ground shakes.
我父亲是神！ 我崇拜我父亲！
My father is God. I worship my father.
由动物保护人士秘密取得
These dramatic videotapes,
内容惊人的录影带 已激起社会大众义愤
secretly obtained by animal rights... activists, have aroused public indignation.
但许多科学家却激烈反对
But many scientists vehemently disagree.
虐待实验
Torture experiments.
我们都是猴子
We're all monkeys.
他们打你？
-  They hurt you?
还没里面那些小兔兔的遭遇惨
Not as bad as what they're doing to the Easter Bunny.
看看它们
Look at them.
人类真该遭到报应
They're just askin' for it.
实验室里的动物…
Animals inside the lab...
或许人类应该被灭绝
Maybe the human race deserves to be wiped out.
灭绝人类？
Wiping out the human race?
这是好主意！ 好主意呀！
It's a great idea. It's great.
但需要长远计划
But more of a long- term thing. First we...
首先我们要专注于眼前的目标
have to focus on more immediate goals.
我可没说那件事哦
I didn't say a word about you- know- what.
你在说什么啊？
What are you talking about?
你的计划啊，大解放！
-  Your plan. Emancipation.
- 你在写什么？ 你是记者？ - 私人事务啦
What are you writing? You a reporter? It's private.
- 诉状吗？ - 私人事务啦
A lawsuit? You gonna sue 'em? -  It's private.
- 你要告他们？ - 嘿，阿詹，该去吃药了
Yo, Jimbo. Time for your meds.
冒冒险，活在当下
Take a chance. Live the moment.
享受阳光和灿烂海滩
Sunshine. Gorgeous beaches.
佛罗里达群岛
The Florida Keys.
佛罗里达群岛- 带你飞向天堂
稍后回到马克斯兄弟的
Monkey Business We'll return you... to the Marx Brothers in Monkey Business.
Monkey Business Monkey business.
Monkey Business
去捡！
Fetch.
懂了吧？猴子，猴、子
Get it? Monkey. Monk key.
猴、匙
Monk key.
什么？
What? -  Shh.
如果未来十年一片惨淡
If you see... a bearish future in the decade ahead,
请考虑横扫世界的改变 和他们所赐予的机会
consider the changes sweeping the world... and the opportunities they offer.
“和他们所赐予的机会”
'And the opportunities they offer.' Ooh.
小詹，他们下了好重的药！
They really dosed you. Jim.
下重药，危险，威尔罗宾森，危险
Major load. Danger, Will Robinson, danger.
你要振作点，清醒一下
You gotta get it together. Focus, focus, focus.
记得那计划吧，我的部分完成了！
Remember the plan. I did my part.
什么？
What? -  Shh.
不是“什么” ，是什么时候
Not 'what,' when.
- 什么时候？ - 这就对啦
When? -  Yes. When.
现在！ 小詹，就是现在！
Now. Now, Jim. Now.
对！ 现在！ 买呀！ 卖呀！
Yes. Now. Buy. Sell.
股票！ 债卷！ 采购！ 卖出！ 对！
Stocks. Bonds. Purchase. Sell.
再也没有欺骗！
Yes. No more monkey business.
- 没有欺骗！ - 我有点晕
No... more... monkey business.
对，强化你的资产目录
Yes, enhance your portfolio now.
五百元，我有五百元 保险有罩我！
Five hundred dollars. I got five hundred dollars. I'm insured.
对！ 机会之窗开了
Yeah. Window of opportunity is opening now.
该让所有好人善加利用时机了 时机！
Now is the time for all good men to seize the moment. The moment.
该让所有好人把握机会了！
Now is the time for all good men to seize the day.
该死的，杰佛瑞！ 少耍蠢了！
Aha. Goddamn it, Jeffrey. Quit playin' the fool.
万事达卡！ 威士卡！
MasterCard. Visa.
快乐之钥！
The key to happiness.
小詹，把握时机！
Jim, seize the moment.
杰佛瑞，给我回来！
Jeffrey, come back here.
- 看在老天份上！ - 杰佛瑞！
For God's sake. -  Jeffrey.
走啊，小詹！
Go, Jim.
Ohh.
- 出去，出去！ - 回来，杰佛瑞！
Get out. Out. -  Come here, Jeffrey.
未来是你的！ 最后机会！ 最后机会！
The future can be yours. Last chance. Last chance.
最后机会！ 最后…
Last chance. Last...
最好的去处是佛罗里达州
Best place to go would be Florida.
这个季节去群岛最棒了
The Keys are lovely this time of year.
…唯一的旅行方式
...it's the only way to travel.
我本想带老婆和孩子的
I was gonna bring along the wife and kiddies,
但杂货店不肯再给一桶
but the grocer couldn't spare another barrel.
我本想带我爷爷，但没地方…
I was gonna bring my grandfather, but there's no room for...
二号今天不能用，用一号
Two's not working today. Use one.
凯瑟琳，这封信在我信箱子里！
Kathryn, this was in my box.
但我有点怀疑，这信不是写给我的
But I have a slight suspicion it wasn't meant for me.
“你是我这辈子砍过最飘亮的女人
'You are the most bootiful woman I have ever seen.
“你活在一个飘亮的世界 你却不知情
You live in a bootiful world, but you don't know it.
“你有自由、阳光和 空气让你呼吸…”
You have freedom, sunshine, air you can breathe...'
詹姆斯柯尔，对吧？
James Cole, right?
“我愿做任何事只求流下来 但我必须离开
'I would do anything to stay her but I must leave. Please help me.'
-  “请帮助我” - 好啦，好啦
Okay, okay, okay. Poor man.
- 可怜的男人 - 嘿，凯瑟琳？
Hey, Kathryn? James Cole is one of yours, right?
詹姆斯柯尔是你的病人吧？ 他逃跑喽，最后被看到是在二楼
He eloped. Last seen, he was up on two.
糟了！
Shit.
我们必须清楚知道那边的情形 才能有所修补
We have to know exactly what's there so we can fix it.
博士，我们有访客
Doctor, we have a visitor.
先生，我能帮你吗？
Um, may I help you? Excuse me?
May I help you? Excuse me?
先生？
Excuse me?
小詹？ 小詹？
Jim? Jim?
嘿，阿詹
Hey, Jimbo.
怎么啦？
What's up, man?
阿詹
Hey, Jimbo.
好，没事了，放轻松
All right, it's okay. Take it easy.
- 没关系的 - 乖哦，放轻松
It'll be all right. -  Take care. Take it easy.
一切都会没事的
Take it easy. We'll work this out, okay?
把你送回房间，喝点牛奶配饼干
Send you back to your room. A little...
你就没事了
milk and cookies, you'll be all right.
放轻松，好吗？
Just take it easy, okay?
镇静点！
Come on. Calm down.
抓住他！ 他妈的抓住他！
Take him down. Take him the fuck down.
我不会伤人
I'm not gonna hurt anyone.
瑞利医生，请帮帮我
Dr. Railly, help me please.
我们得替你注射，让你镇静下来
We're gonna give you something to calm you, James.
不！ 不要打药了！
No. No more drugs.
詹姆斯，我们非做不可 你太昏乱了
James, we have to do this. You're very confused.
不要打药！ 住手！
No drugs. Stop it.
凯瑟琳，我们合作四年了
Kathryn, we've been working together for...
我从没看过你这样
four years. I've never seen you like this.
拜托防御心别那么重 我又不是在审讯你
So please stop being so defensive. This isn't an inquisition.
我又没有防御心重，只是想解释…
I didn't think I was being defensive. I was trying to explain exactly what...
不应该关住他
He should've been in restraints.
那摆明就是你判断错误 为什么不直接承认呢？
It was bad judgment on your part, plain and simple. Why not own up to it?
好吧，我判断错误 但我对他有种很怪的感觉
Okay, it was bad judgment, but I have... the strangest feeling about him.
我在哪里见过他，而且…
I've seen him someplace, and I'm trying...
两名警察已经住院了
Two policemen are in the hospital.
现在又有一名保安人员头颅破裂
Now we've got a security guard with a skull fracture.
我说过我判断错误了嘛！ 你还要我说什么？
I said it was bad judgment. What else do you want me to say?
看到没？ 懂我意思吧？
You see that? See what I mean?
你防御心太重，她是不是这样？
You're being defensive. Isn't she being defensive?
- 佛雷薛医生？ - 什么事？
Dr. Fletcher?
又有状况了
What? -  Ah, we have... another situation.
他被关着而且全身锁住？
He was fully restrained and the door was locked?
是，长官，我亲自上的锁
Yes, sir. I did it myself.
而且打了镇静剂？
And he was fully sedated?
打了镇静剂
He was fully sedated.
所以你是说，一个打了镇静剂 全身被锁住的病人
Then, are you trying to tell me a fully... sedated, fully restrained patient...
竟然有办法从排气孔溜出去 再把铁网放回来
somehow slipped out that vent, replaced the grill behind him...
现在正在排气管里乱钻？
and is wriggling his way through the ventilation system?
小心！
Watch it.
你真的搞砸了！
You sure fucked up.
- 你在哪里？ - 你会说话！
Where are you? -  Ah, you can talk.
小巴比，你做了啥，自愿啦？
What'd you do, Bobby boy?
- 我不叫巴比 - 没问题，巴比
My name's not Bob.
他们为什么派你来？
Not a prob, Bob. Where'd they send you?
- 你在哪里？ - 另一间囚室
Where are you? Another cell.
也许
Maybe.
什么叫 “也许” ？ 那是什么意思？
What do you mean 'maybe'? What's that supposed to mean?
也许就是说
Maybe means...
也许我在隔壁囚室
maybe I'm in the next cell.
跟你一样是志愿者
Another volunteer like you.
也许我在总部
Or maybe I'm in the Central Office...
替那些科学怪人监视你
spying on ya for all those science bozos.
或者，也许我根本不在这里
Or hey, maybe I'm not even here.
也许我只是在你脑中
Maybe I'm just in your head.
完全无法确定
No way to confirm anything.
他们把你送到哪里去了？
Where'd they send ya? -  1990.
- 1990年 - 1990！ 那边怎样？
'90. How was it?
货很纯吧？ 一堆辣妹？
Good drugs? Lots of pussy?
巴比，你完成任务没？
Hey, Bob, you do the job?
你有没有找到大消息？
You find out the big info?
十二猴子军？
Army of the Twelve Monkeys?
应该去1996年的
It was supposed to be 1996.
没有这群小丑，科学就不叫科学了
Science ain't an exact science with these clowns,
但他们在进步了
but they're getting better.
你没被送往古埃及就该偷笑了
You're lucky you didn't end up in ancient Egypt.
他们来了
Shh. They're comin'.
第二街上的动物解放协会
The Freedom for Animals Association on Second Avenue...
就是十二猴子军的秘密基地
is the secret headquarters... of the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
他们将会做出那件事
They are the ones who are going to do it.
我帮不上忙了，得走了
I can't do any more. I have to go now.
圣诞快乐
Have a merry Christmas.
- 怎么样？ - 什么？
Well? -  What?
你有没有录下这段留言？
Did you or did you not record that message?
我们把劣质的录音重整过
It's a reconstruction of a deteriorated recording.
讯号很弱
Weak signal. We have to...
一次只能拼凑一个字
put them together one word at a time.
我们才刚刚把讯息拼好 你有没有打这通电话？
We just finished rebuilding this. Did you or did you not make this call?
我没办法打电话
I couldn't make any call. You sent me...
你们把我送错年代了，那是1990年
to the wrong year. It was 1990.
- 1990？ - 1990？
1990? -  1990?
你确定？
You're certain of that?
柯尔，你在那边做了什么？
What'd you do with your time, Cole?
你把时间浪费在嗑药还是女人上？
Did you waste it on drugs? Women?
他们逼我吃药
They forced me to take drugs. -  Forced you?
逼你？为什么会有人要逼你吃药？
Why would someone force you to take drugs?
我惹了麻烦，被逮捕了
I was in trouble. I... got arrested.
我…
I... I did what you wanted.
我做了你们要做的事 我抓了一个标本，一只蜘蛛
I got a specimen, a spider.
我没地方放，只好吃掉
I didn't have anyplace to put it, so I ate it.
但你们把我送错年代了 所以其实都不重要了
But you sent me to the wrong year, so it really doesn't matter.
你回来时有没有看到这个？
Did you see this when you went back?
我想没有，长官
No, sir, I don't think so.
这些人呢？ 你有没有看到他们？
What about these people? Did you see any of these people?
没有
No.
噢，等一下
Oh, wait, wait.
他？
Him?
你看到他了？
You saw that man?
好像是在精神病院里
Maybe in the... maybe in the mental institution.
你进了精神病院？
You were in a mental institution?
天哪！
Oh, God.
柯尔，我们是派你去做重要观察的
Cole, you were sent back to make some very important observations.
你并没有做出贡献
You could've made a real contribution.
帮助我们重新回到地球
Helped us to reclaim the planet.
也没能灭短刑期
As well as reducing your sentence.
柯尔，我问你 你要不要再一次机会？
The question is, Cole, do you want another chance?
好
Good.
最后连接开始
Last connection going on.
让开
-  Stand clear.
- 他是你选的 - 现在已经来不及了
He was your choice. Nothing we can do about that now.
柯尔，这次别出错了
No mistakes this time, Cole.
小心点，睁大眼看
Stay alert. Keep your eyes open.
抓蜘蛛一事你做得很对 想办法再做点类似的事
Good thinking about the spider. Try and do something like that again.
现在放轻松，不要抗拒
Just relax now. Don't fight it.
我们要把你送往1996年后期 正是我们要的时间
We're sending you to the third quarter of 1996. Right on the money.
什么？ 我听不懂！
What? I don't understand.
我在哪里？
Where am I?
我要找他们！ 要找他们！
I gotta find 'em. I gotta find 'em.
救命！ 我不知道我在哪里！
Help. I don't know where I am.
你要帮我找到他们！
You gotta help me find 'em. -  Jose?
荷西？ 荷西！
Jose. -  Cole.
柯尔，我们在哪里？
Cole, where are we? Where are we?
- 柯尔！ - 荷西！
Jose. -  Help me, Cole.
- 帮我，柯尔！ - 天啊！ 等一下！
Oh, God. Wait.
布特罗斯厅
巴尔的摩- 1996年11月
“在传染病风行之时 都会出现不少预兆和占卜
'In a season of great pestilence,
今晚- 凯瑟琳瑞利医生 疯狂与天眼通
there are omens and divinations.
“四活物中有一个给了那七位天使
And one of the four beasts gave unto the seven angels...
“七个盛满神谴的金碗
seven golden vials full of the wrath of God,
“神永生不朽”
who liveth forever and ever.'
启示录
Revelations.
十四世纪，根据当时的记载
In the fourteenth century, according to the... accounts of local officials of that time,
这个人突然出现在 巨石柱群附近的威尔村
this man appeared suddenly in... the village of Wyle near Stonehenge...
时间是1362年4月
in April of 1362.
他使用陌生的字眼，以怪异的腔调
Using unfamiliar words and speaking in a strange accent,
说出有关瘟疫的迫切预兆
the man made dire prognostications... about a pestilence...
他说6百年后瘟疫将毁灭人类
which he said would wipe out humanity... in approximately 600 years.
显然，所谓的瘟疫末日现象 若有事实加持
Obviously, this plague- doomsday scenario... is more compelling...
就更令人信服了，一场致命疾病
when reality supports it with a virulent disease,
无论是鼠疫、天花或爱滋病
whether it's the bubonic plague, smallpox or AIDS.
现在我们又有了科技恐慌 如化学武器
Now we have technological horrors, such as chemical warfare,
它首次出现于
which reared its ugly head during the...
一次世界大战的毒气攻击
deadly mustard gas attacks of World War I.
1917年10月的那场战役中 在法国战壕里
During such an attack in... the French trenches in October of 1917,
我们找到了这名士兵
we have an account of this soldier, who,
他在袭击中被炮弹碎片打伤
during an assault, was wounded by shrapnel...
被送进医院，情绪变得歇斯底里
and hospitalized, apparently in a state of hysteria.
医生发现他丧失所有法语理解力
Doctors found that he had lost all comprehension of French,
但却说着一口流利的英语
but that he spoke English fluently,
而且还能说他们并不熟悉的方言
albeit in a regional dialect they didn't recognize.
这男人的身体并未受毒气影响
The man, though physically unaffected by the gas,
心智却失常了
was beside himself.
他宣称他来自未来
He claimed that he had come from the future...
而且要寻找一种原菌
that he was looking for a pure germ...
这个原菌将自1996年起
that would ultimately wipe mankind... off the face of the Earth...
使人类从地球表面完全灭绝
starting in the year 1996.
这位受了伤的年轻士兵 在医院里失踪了
Though injured, the young soldier disappeared from the hospital,
显然想继续完成警告他人的未完使命
no doubt trying to carry on his mission to warn others,
将对战争的焦虑转化为
and substituting for the agony of war...
自我焦虑 我们称之为“卡桑德拉情结”
a self- inflicted agony we call the 'Cassandra Complex.'
在希腊传说里 卡桑德拉遭到通晓未来
Cassandra, in Greek legend, was condemned to know the future...
却在预示他人时不被相信的惩罚
but to be disbelieved when she foretold it.
因此，拥有预知能力
Hence, the agony of foreknowledge combined...
却对未来无能为力相结合成焦虑
with the impotence to do anything about it.
我要立刻去注射疫苗
I'm going right out to get vaccinated.
嗨
Hi.
瑞利博士，你让危言耸听的人 都无地自容呢
I think, Dr. Railly, you've given the alarmists a bad name.
有吗？
I have?
有真实而令人信服的证据
-  Mm- hmm. Surely there's very real and convincing data...
显示地球无法撑过人口过度膨胀啊
that the planet cannot survive the excesses of the human race.
没错
This is true.
核子武器的扩建 失控的繁衍习惯
Proliferation of atomic devices, uncontrolled breeding habits,
土地、海洋和空气污染 对环境大加凌虐
pollution of land, sea and air, the rape of the environment.
在这种状况下，四眼天鸡 代表有理智的远见不是很明显吗？
In this context, isn't it obvious that Chicken Little represents the sane vision,
而现代人的座右铭：“我们去血拼”
and that Homo sapiens' motto, 'Let's go shopping,'
不也是完全疯狂的呼喊吗？
is the cry of the true lunatic?
凯瑟琳，我叫特洛伊
Kathryn, it's time. -  My name is Troy.
瑞利医生 不晓得你是否知道我的研究
Please, Dr. Railly. I wonder if you're aware of my own studies.
明天上班见
See you at work tomorrow.
再打电话给你
Give you a call tomorrow.
不！ 不！
No. No. Get in the car.
上车，快上车，我有枪
Get in the car. I've got a gun. Get in the car.
好，开车
All right, drive.
拿走我的钱包 我有很多现金和信用卡
Take my purse. I've got a lot of cash...
- 车钥匙给你！ - 快发动！
and credit cards. Take my keys. Start the car.
不！
No.
这里右转，右转！
Here, turn right. Turn right here.
- 我们要去哪里？ - 费城
Wh- Where are we going? Philadelphia.
- 那超过150公里耶！ - 所以我才不能用走的
That's more than a hundred miles. That's why I can't walk there. -  Just let me go.
- 请放我走 - 开车！
Just drive. -  You can take the car.
- 车子给你 - 我不会开车
I don't know how to drive.
我八岁时就到地下去了
I went underground when I was eight...
我告诉过你的
years old. I told you that before.
下一个转角右转
At the next corner, turn right.
柯尔，詹姆斯柯尔
Cole. James Cole.
六年前你从上锁的房间里逃走
You escaped from a locked room six years ago.
对你是六年
Six years for you.
- 右转，继续开！ - 好
Turn around. Get goin'. -  Okay.
柯尔先生，我不相信这是巧合
I can't believe that this is a coincidence, Mr. Cole.
你一直在跟踪我吗？
Have you been following me? -  You said you would help me.
你说会帮我，我知道你只是嘴上说说
I know this isn't what you meant,
但我身上没钱
but I don't have any money.
腿又受伤，之前都睡在大街上
I hurt my leg, and I've been sleeping on the street.
我一定也全身发臭
I'm sure I smell bad. Do you have any food in this car?
你车里有吃的吗？ 你一直在跟踪我，对不对？
You have been following me, haven't you?
没有
No.
我看到了这个
No, I saw this...
在商店橱窗里
in a store window.
我会认字，记得吧？
I can read, remember? -  Uh- huh.
凯瑟琳瑞利医生 11月19号- 晚上8点
记得
Yeah.
你为什么要去费城？
Why do you want to go to Philadelphia?
我查过巴尔的摩的资料 啥都没有
I checked out the Baltimore information. It was nothing.
其实是在费城 那些动手的人，他们就在那里
It's in Philadelphia. That's where they are, the ones who did it.
十二猴子
The Twelve Monkeys.
- 那是收音机吗？ - 对
Is that a radio? -  Yeah.
能不能打开？
Can you... turn it on?
这是一封给您的私人讯息
This is a personal message to you.
您束手无策了吗？ 您渴望逃脱吗？
Are you at the end of your rope? Are you dying to get away?
佛罗里达群岛正在等您
The Florida Keys are waiting for you.
- 海浪… - 我从来没看过大海
Ocean waves... I've never seen the ocean.
柯尔先生，那是广告
It's an advertisement, Mr. Cole.
什么？
What is?
那是广告，你应该懂吧？
It's an advertisement. You do understand that?
并不是真正给你的特别讯息
It's not really a special message to you.
柯尔先生
Mr. Cole.
- 你以前都叫我詹姆斯 - 你喜欢那样吗？
You used to call me James. -  You prefer that?
詹姆斯，你不是真的有枪吧
James, uh, you don't really have a gun.
能不能开大声点？
Can you turn this up? Can you make this louder?
我心悸动
在蓝莓坡
当我与你相遇
我好喜欢二十世纪的音乐！
Ah, I love the music of the twentieth century.
好喜欢这空气！ 喜欢呼吸这空气！
I love this air. Love to breathe this air.
北向 雀斯特- 费城
WXBX news break.
WXBX新闻时间，即时新闻 记者罗杰普拉特为您报导
News as it happens. Roger Pratt reporting.
最新消息
A story breaking with us now is emergency...
急救小组正赶往一处玉米田
crews are converging on a cornfield...
九岁男孩瑞克纽曼的玩伴说 看到纽曼在他们眼前消失
where playmates of nine- year- old Ricky Neuman... say they saw him disappear right before their eyes.
小纽曼显然掉入了荒弃的竖井
Young Neuman apparently stepped into an abandoned well shaft,
被困在长45公尺的狭窄管道中
and is lodged somewhere in the narrow 150- foot pipe.
可能还活着，可能受了重伤
Possibly alive, possibly seriously injured,
玩伴宣称听到他微弱的呼救声
playmates claim they heard him cry out faintly.
- 不要喊狼来了 - 什么
Never cry wolf. -  What?
我爸说的，他说 “不要喊狼来了”
My father said that to me. He said, 'Never cry wolf.'
因为等到真的有事发生 就没人会相信你了
'Cause then people won't believe you... if something really happens.
詹姆斯，像怎样的事会发生？
If something really happens like what, James?
坏事
Something bad. Can we have some more...
能不能多听点音乐？ 我不想听这个
music? I don't wanna hear this stuff.
能不能多听点音乐？
Can we hear more music?
我看到绿树
噢，好棒
Oh, that's good.
还有红玫瑰
我看过花朵绽放
为你和我
而我暗想
这世界真美好
瑞利医生？你好 我是精神病患柜的魏克
Hello, Dr. Railly? Yeah, this is Wikke from Psyche Admitting.
记得詹姆斯柯尔吗？ 在1990年无故消失的焦虑症患者？
Do you remember James Cole? The paranoid who pulled the Houdini back in '90?
他回来了，而且…
Well, he's back and...
抱歉，他在找你，我想该让你知道
Sorry about that. He's looking for you. I thought you ought to know.
好，保重
All right, take care.
就跟我告诉你的一样
-  It's like I told you.
我和我先生先离开，但她一直没来
Me and my husband went ahead and she never showed.
这不像她的作风
That is totally unlike her.
你知道她开什么车吗？
Do you know the make of her car? -  Um...
94年的银色休旅车
Cherokee. '94 Cherokee, silver.
绿洲旅社 我做“倒” 了
I have 'doed- it.'
我做“倒” 了，对
I have 'done doed- it'. Ja.
我，葛森费柏教授 发明了时光隧道！
I, Professor Grossenfibber, have invented the time tunnel.
天啊！
Oh, boy.
抱歉，先生，抽根雪茄吧
Oh, excuse me, mister.
Excuse me, mister. Have a cigar.
不！
No.
现在我的时光机可以开始做实验了
Now my time machine is ready for experiments.
啄木鸟！ 对！
Ah, the woodpecker. Ja.
哈，啄木鸟！ 快回来！
Yo- hoo, Woodpecker.
你刚才在我梦里
You were in my dream just now.
你的头发不一样，是另一种颜色
Your hair's different. Different color.
我确定那是你
I'm sure it was you.
关于什么的梦？
What was the dream about?
在机场
About an airport...
在一切发生之前
before everything happened.
我每次都做同样的梦，在我小时候
It's the same dream I always have. When I was a kid.
我都在梦里？
And I was in it?
我在做什么？
What did I do?
你很伤心
You were very upset.
你在梦里总是很伤心
You're always very upset in the dream.
我只是一直不知道是你
Just never knew it was you.
詹姆斯，之前那并不是我
-  It wasn't me before, James.
现在因为发生的事，才变成是我
It's become me now because of what's happening.
能不能把我松绑？
Could you please untie me?
不，我认为一直都是你
No, I think it was always you.
很奇怪
Very strange.
你脸发红，之前还在呻吟 我想你在发烧
You're flushed, and you were moaning. I think you're running a fever.
你在干嘛？
What are you doing?
在加州佛雷斯诺
In Fresno, California, crews continue to...
急救小组仍试图拯救九岁的瑞克纽曼
attempt to rescue nine- year- old Ricky Neuman.
回到本地新闻 巴尔的摩的凯瑟琳瑞利
And closer to home, in Baltimore, Kathryn Railly,
她是著名的精神科医生 最近还出版了有关疯狂的新作
prominent psychiatrist and the author... of a newly released book on insanity,
昨晚在大学的一场演讲之后神秘失踪
disappeared mysteriously last night... after a lecture at the university.
瑞利医生失踪一案 警方要求前精神病患詹姆斯柯尔
Former mental patient, James Cole, is wanted for questioning...
到案说明
regarding Dr. Railly's disappearance.
警方警告民众，柯尔有暴力前科
Authorities warn that Cole has a history of violence...
并建议任何看到他的民众 立刻通知警方
and advise anyone spotting him to notify authorities at once.
好喜欢这音乐
Love this music.
我们都没有，类似的东西都没有
We don't have this. We don't have anything like this.
这些是什么纸？
What are all those?
这些？
-  These?
是我的笔记，线索
My notes. Clues.
什么线索？
What kind of clues? -  It's about the secret army.
跟秘密军有关的，就是十二猴子军
The Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
他们是散播病毒的人 我就是因此才过来的
They're the ones that spread the virus. That's why I'm here.
我得找出他们，这是我的任务
I have to find them. That's my mission.
我只需要弄清他们的位置 因为他们有种原病毒
I just have to locate them because they have...
之后就会变种
the virus in its pure form before it mutates.
等我找到，他们就会派科学家过来
When I locate them, they'll send a scientist here.
那位科学家会研究那个病毒
That scientist will study the virus.
然后他会回到现代
Then when he goes back to the present,
跟其他科学家一起想出解药
he and the scientists will make a cure.
…来自三辖区的员警 包括特殊作战部队的人员
...police officers from three jurisdictions, including special tactical unit personnel,
都已动员前往控制 数量愈增的围观民众
have now been mobilized to control... the growing thousands of onlookers...
在加州佛雷斯诺…
in Fresno, California... -  Does that disturb you?
- 听这个会让你心烦吗？ - 不会 我以为跟我们有关
No. I thought it was about us.
我以为也许他们会围捕我们 然后逮捕我
I thought maybe they'd captured us... and arrested me.
开玩笑的
Just a joke. Hmm.
我记得我很担心那位小男孩
I remember being very afraid for that little boy.
独自一人陷在井里 不知道会不会有人来救他
All alone, down that well, not knowing... if anybody's gonna get him out.
那是我在小时候第一次这么害怕
The first time I was ever really afraid when I was a kid.
什么叫做你在小时候？
What do you mean, when you were a kid?
不重要啦，这只是唬人的恶作剧 那小孩躲在谷仓里
Never mind. Just a prank, a hoax. That boy's hiding in a barn.
地球死了
“有不少预兆和占卜
'There are omens and divinations.
“四活物中有一个给了那七位天使
One of the four beasts gave unto the seven angels...
“七个盛满神谴的金碗
seven golden vials full of the wrath of God,
“神永生不朽”
who liveth forever and ever.'
等到下个月大家开始死亡 你就不会认为我是疯子了
You won't think I'm crazy... when people start dying next month.
一开始大家以为只是某种怪感冒
First they'll think it's just some weird fever.
然后就会知道
Then they'll find out.
他们会明白怎么回事
They'll catch on.
等等！ 停！ 停车！ 在这里停车！
Wait. Stop here. Stop the car. Stop right here.
我说对了！ 他们在这里！
I was right. They're here.
看到没？ 十二猴子
You see? Twelve Monkeys. Twelve Monkeys.
十二猴子，现在你相信我了吧？ 来啊！
Do you believe me now? Come on.
来啊！
Come on.
他们在这里！ 看到没？ 十二猴子！
They're here. You see? Twelve Monkeys.
十二猴子，来看
Twelve Monkeys. Come on.
十二猴子
Twelve Monkeys.
等一下
Wait, wait, wait. Wait, here.
你看，看到没？ 看到没？
Here. Do you see it? Do you see?
- 我看到红漆和一些记号 - 记号？你以为这是…
I see some red paint, some marks. Marks? Marks? Do you think that...
太荒唐了
-  Oh, this is ridicu...
- 喂！ 喂！ - 干嘛？
Hey. Hey. -  What?
你不准做蠢事
Don't you do anything crazy...
否则我会伤人
or I'll hurt somebody.
我不会做蠢事 但这些都跟你想的不同
I am not gonna do anything crazy, but... none of this is what you think it is.
你躲不掉的，巴比
You can't hide from them, Bob.
我说你躲不掉的
I said, you can't hide from them.
不，长官，老巴比
No, sir, ol' Bob.
试都别试了
Don't even try.
他们什么都听得到
They hear everything.
你身上装有追踪设备
They got that tracking device on ya.
他们随时随地都找得到你
They can find you anywhere, anytime.
是在牙齿里，对吧？ 巴比？
It's in the tooth. Right, Bob?
但我骗过他们了，老兄
But I fooled 'em, old buddy.
他们不需要监视我 我在做该做的事
They don't have to spy on me. I'm doing what I'm supposed to be doing.
看到没？ 又有了
You see? Here it is again.
看，跟着这到漆痕
Here, follow this paint trail.
就在这里，看到没？
Here. It's here. See?
- 好可怕！ 我… - 不！ 跟我来！
It's so awful. I... -  No, no, no. Come with me.
- 可恶！ - 漆痕到了这里
Damn it. -  The paint trail goes here.
放手！ 放开我的手！ 詹姆斯，我们不该进来
Let go. Let go of my arm. James, we shouldn't be here.
该死的！
Goddamn it.
放开我！
Leave me alone.
我们出去吧
Let's get outta here.
詹姆斯，我们不该进来
James, we shouldn't be here.
嘿！
Hey.
拜托别杀我！ 别杀我，求求你！
Please, don't kill me.
别杀我，别杀我
Don't kill me. Please. Don't kill me. Don't kill me.
别动，婊子
Stick around, bitch.
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
他还活着吗？
Is he alive?
来吧，我们没时间了 你救不了他！
Come on. We're runnin' out of time.
天哪！ 詹姆斯，你杀了他！
You can't help him. -  Oh, Jesus. James, you killed him.
我眼中只看到死人，走吧
All I see are dead people. Come on.
走吧
Come on.
你一直都没有枪
-  You never had a gun before.
现在有了，快走
I have one now. Come on. Come on.
“…必在它华美殿内吼叫”
'...dragons in their pleasant palaces.
“第七位天使把碗倒在空中
The seventh angel poured out...
“就有…”你！
his vial into the air, and there came...'
你！
You. You.
你也是我们之中的一个！
You're one of us.
就是这个
This is it.
快来！
Come on.
有什么事吗？
Um... can we help you?
只是录音带
It's just a tape.
我要找十二猴子军
I'm looking for the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
我们一点也不知道十二猴子军的事
We don't know anything about any Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
所以你和你朋友可以走了
So you and your friend just disappear.
我只想要点资料
I just want some information.
- 你没听到我的话，我说… - 别伤害她
Didn't you hear me? I sa... -  Don't hurt her.
拜托，我是精神科医生 请照他的话做
Please, I'm a psychiatrist. J- Just do whatever he tells you to do.
他精神失常，很危险
He's disturbed. He's dangerous.
求求你们合作
Please, just cooperate.
你要什么？钱吗？ 我们只有几块钱
What do you want, money? We only got a few bucks.
我说过我要什么了
I told you what I want.
趴下，锁上门！
Get down. Lock that door.
- 詹姆斯，别… - 锁门！
-  James, don't... Lock it now.
我说过那个疯子戈恩会让我们…
I told you fucking Goines would get us...
闭嘴！
Shut up.
戈恩？
Goines?
杰佛瑞戈恩？
Jeffrey Goines?
然后杰佛瑞成了大人物 媒体争相报导
Then Jeffrey becomes this big star, and the media latch onto him because...
因为他挑选自己的父亲 一位有名的诺贝尔奖病毒学得主
he's picketing his own father, a famous Nobel prize- winning virologist.
你一定在电视上看过
You must've seen all that on TV.
我不看电视
-  I don't watch TV.
是他吗？
Is this him?
对，就是他，就是他
Yeah, that's him. That's him.
你准备拿我们怎么办？
What are you gonna do to us?
多说点杰佛瑞的事
Tell me more about Jeffrey.
杰佛瑞开始厌倦我们的做法
Jeffrey started getting bored with the shit we do.
巡逻、发传单、写信之类的
Picketing, leafleting, letter- writing stuff.
他说我们是徒劳无功的自由混帐
He said we were ineffectual, liberal jerk- offs.
他想进行一场大行动来教育社会大众
He wanted to do guerrilla actions in order to educate the public.
像这样？
Like this?
参议员大受惊吓
Yeah. That's when he let 100 snakes loose in the Senate.
对，他那次放了100只蛇到参议院
But we weren't into that kind of stuff.
但我们不做那种事 这样会招致恶果，我们告诉过他了
It's counterproductive. We told him.
于是他和另11人
So he and 11 guys,
分头组织了这个地下军队
they split off and formed this underground army.
十二猴子军
The Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
看吧？
See?
开始计划“猎捕人类”行动
They started planning a 'Human Hunt.'
买了玩具枪、网子和捕熊陷阱
They bought stun guns, nets and bear traps.
他们要到华尔街去抓律师和银行家…
They were gonna go to Wall Street and trap lawyers and bankers...
当然结果并没有做 他们什么都没做
They didn't do it, of course. They didn't do any of it.
就跟以往一样 大人物先生总是出卖朋友
Like always, Mr. Big Shot sold his friends out.
那是什么意思？
What does that mean?
他上电视，开记者会，昭告全世界
He goes on TV and gives a news... conference. Tells the whole world...
说他刚发觉他老爸的实验 对全人类很重要
he just realized his daddy's experiments... are vital for humanity...
而用动物是绝对有必要的
and that the use of animals is absolutely necessary.
而他从现在起要亲自督导实验室
And that from now on he, Jeffrey Goines, is going to personally supervise the labs...
确保那些小动物不会受苦
to make sure the little animals aren't going to suffer.
这是什么？
What is this?
爱护动物- 别吃它们
吃肉是谋杀
不可能接近那种大人物的
People like that aren't accessible,
你不可以擅闯，这样是行不通的
okay? You can't just barge in on them.
安静点，好好开车 我知道自己在做什么
It's not how the world works. Be quiet and drive the car. I know what I'm doing.
不，你不知道，这部车是你偷来的
No, you don't. This car is stolen.
我们惹出大麻烦了，大麻烦
And we are in big trouble. Big trouble.
如果你不自首，他们会杀掉你的
If you don't turn yourself over, the police are...
他们也会杀我 因为我成了谋杀案帮凶
going to kill you. They're going to shoot me too, 'cause I'm going to be the accessory to murder.
- 你们全都会死 - 没有人会死
You're all going to die. Nobody is going to die.
你不可能救得了世界
You're not going to save the world.
懂吗？ 你在幻想
Okay? You're delusional.
你用脑子里的片段编出这一切
You've made all this up out of bits and pieces in your head.
- 不 - 就是
No. Yes.
我给你举个例子
Let me give you an example.
你认识杰佛瑞戈恩 你们都是郡立精神病院的病人
You know Jeffrey Goines. You were...
杰佛瑞戈恩是个疯子
both patients at County Hospital. Jeffrey Goines was a fruitcake.
当时他告诉你
He told you then his father was a...
他父亲是有名的科学家 研究病毒的
famous scientist who worked with viruses.
你就把这个资讯放进了荒唐的幻想
You've incorporated that bit... of information to this cockeyed fantasy.
他没说他父亲是科学家 他只说他父亲是神
He didn't say his father was a... scientist. He said his father was God.
真疯狂
This is insane.
…有名的精神科医生和作家 凯瑟琳瑞利医生
...prominent psychiatrist and author.
遭到危险精神病患绑架
Dr. Kathryn Railly, has been abducted by...
该病患名叫詹姆斯柯尔 六年前是瑞利的病人
a dangerous mental patient, James Cole. Cole was under Railly's care six years...
当时他巧妙地逃脱…
ago when he made a dramatic escape from...
你的腿怎么了？
What is the matter with your leg?
被枪打中
-  I got shot.
枪！ 谁开枪射你？
Shot. Who shot you?
I don't know.
不知道，在某一场战争里，不重要啦
It was some kind of war. Never mind.
反正你不会相信我
You wouldn't believe me anyway.
你做什么？
What are you doing?
我们不需要加油
We don't need gas.
我以为你不会开车
I thought you didn't know how to drive.
我说我太小还不能开车 并没说我是笨蛋
I said I was too young to drive. I didn't say I was stupid.
不能这样下去，如果你腿上中弹 我就得做些处理
This can't go on. If you have a bullet... in your leg, I have to take care of it.
我是医生，我需要一些医疗用品
I'm a doctor. I need some supplies.
同时，在加州佛雷斯诺
Meanwhile, in Fresno, California,
采矿工程师持续迫切地钻打一条竖井
where mining engineers continue their... desperate attempt to sink a shaft...
跟九岁男孩瑞克纽曼 受困的那条平行
parallel to the one in which nine- year- old Ricky Neuman is believed trapped.
警方说那男孩仍有机会…
Authorities say there is still a chance the boy might be...
你不该在这条腿上施力 应该要缝起来，吃点抗生素
You shouldn't put your weight on it. You need stitches and antibiotics.
幸好伤口靠近表皮
Lucky for you it's near the surface.
我好喜欢看太阳
I love seeing the sun.
等等！
Ooh. -  Wait.
让我扶你
Let me help you.
你好香
You smell so good.
你最好自首
You have to give yourself up.
这你知道吧？
Y- You know that, don't you?
你干什么？ 詹姆斯？
W- What are you doing? James?
对不起
I'm sorry.
你干什么？
-  What are you doing?
詹姆斯，住手！ 你干什么？
James, stop it. What are you doing? I'm sorry.
- 放开我！ - 我必须这么做
Let go of me. -  I have to do this.
- 找到他了？ - 谁？
They find him? -  Who?
那孩子，困在管道里的
That kid. The one in the pipe. -  You believe that?
相信吗？ 他们放了一只猴子下去
They're lowering a monkey down there and a...
猴子身上绑了一架迷你红外线摄影机
miniature infrared camera strapped on him,
一块用铝箔纸包的烤牛肉三明治
and a roast beef sandwich wrapped up in tin foil.
- 你乱编的吧 - 没有，是真的，生命真的很怪
You're making it up. No, I shit you not. Life is really weird.
猴子和烤牛肉三明治
A monkey and a roast beef sandwich.
我能享受这顿丰美的晚餐
W- W- Would that I could enjoy this opulent dinner...
最令人振奋欣喜的同伴
and this most, uh, stimulatin' and excitin' company...
因为其本身并没有目的
for itself with no sense of purpose.
但是啊，我好苦恼
But, alas, I am burdened.
因为随着大众对我的关注 和赞赏而来的
For with all this excess of public... attention and cacophony of praise...
是重大的责任
there comes great responsibility.
我无须说明
I don't have to tell you all that the dangers of science...
说科学危险是句陈腔滥调了
are a timeworn threat.
从普罗米修斯从诸神那里窃取火…
From Prometheus stealin' fire from the gods...
- 什么朋友？ 我没在等人啊 - …到核弹恐怖的
What friend? I'm not expectin' anyone.
…冷战时期，但过去从未…
to the Cold War era of the Dr. Strangelove terror.
真是荒唐
But never before... -  This is ridiculous.
我父亲正在做重大演讲
My father's giving a major address.
…畏惧着
...to fear the power...
我们掌中的权力
we have at hand.
通常，若抓到这种没带身分证 鬼鬼祟祟乱逛的人
Normally, if we caught a guy sneakin' around... like this with no I.D., we'd bust his ass.
我们会狠揍他一顿，抱歉我的用词
Excuse my French.
这人说他认识你
This one says he knows you.
由于你似乎有不少特殊的朋友
Since you seem to have had a few unusual associates,
我们当然不想逮捕你的亲密伙伴
we certainly would not want to arrest one of your closest pals.
这辈子从没见过他
Never seen him before in my life.
你们想怎么虐待这个人都可以
Feel free to torture this man, or whatever it is you do.
我要回去听父亲的滔滔演说…
I'm going to listen to my father's eloquent discourse on...
我来这里是为了猴子的事
I'm here about some monkeys.
- 猴子？ - 对，猴子
Monkeys? -  Monkeys. Yes.
有十二只
Twelve of them.
阿诺
Arnold.
- 你看来真惨耶 - 你认识这个人？
You look like shit. -  You know this man?
我当然认识他，阿诺派迪博
I know this man. Arnold... Pettibone. Mm- hmm.
小诺，不是说要穿西装打领带的吗 我说你有空来看我
Gee, Arnie. It's black tie. I said drop by,
但现在是我爸的大场面耶 有贵宾、参议员和情报局
but it's Dad's big do... V.I.P. s, senators, Secret Service.
你饿不饿，小诺？
You hungry, Arnie?
今晚有大餐喔 很多死羊、死牛和死猪
Killer feast we're putting on tonight. Lots of dead lamb, dead cow, dead pig.
Shall we?
嗨，你好吗？ 真迷人
Hi. How are you? Hello.
1990年“大逃亡”
Very attractive. 'The Great Escape,' 1990.
小心点！
Watch it. Huh?
什么？郡立医院？ 我说对了？
County Hospital? Am I right?
我没办法阻止你准备做的事
I can't do anything about what you're...
我无法改变
going to do. I can't change anything.
我阻止不了你
I can't stop you. I just want the information.
- 我只是要一点资料 - 我们得谈谈，来
We need to talk. C'mon.
女士们好，真高兴看到你们 下楼时请小心阶梯
Hi, ladies. Nice to see you again. Watch your step on the way down.
谁泄露的？ 布鲁？ 韦勒？
Who blabbed? Bruhns? Weller?
- 我只是想取得原病毒 - 病毒？
I just want access to the pure virus.
为了未来，我需要知道 病毒在哪里、到底是什么病毒
Virus? For the future. I need to know where it is and exactly what it is.
懂了，我知道你想干嘛 还是老计划对吧？
Ahh, I get it. I see what you're up to. It's your old plan, isn't it? -  What plan?
- 什么计划？ - 你的计划啊，记得吗？
Your plan. Remember?
我不知道你在说什么
I don't know what you're talking about.
你知道，当时我们在休息室看电视
Yes, you do. We were in the dayroom... watching television...
你对地球受到亵渎感到沮丧 这点我很能理解
and you were upset about the desecration... of the planet, which I understand.
然后你对我说
Then you said to me, 'Wouldn't it...
“要是有种细菌或病毒 能把全人类全杀光
be great if there was a germ or virus...
“只留下动物和树木，那该有多好”
that would wipe out all of mankind and leave the animals and trees?'
- 你想把我搞昏 - 你超好笑的
You're trying to confuse me. -  You were so funny.
我对你说，我父亲是有名的病毒学家
I told you my father was...
你就说：“他可以做出细菌 我们就去偷”
this famous virologist, and you said, 'He could make a germ, and we could...
真是有够疯
steal it.' Coo- coo- ka- roo, you were.
病毒变种了！ 我们躲到地下！
They mutate. We live underground.
全世界由动物统治
The world belongs to the dogs and cats.
我们活得像条虫
We live like worms.
- 我只是需要资讯 - 放轻松啦
I just need the information.
你根本就是个疯子！ 完全癫狂、精神有病
Take it easy. You are a total nutcase. Completely deranged.
你的处理器坏掉啦
Delusional, paranoid. Your process is all fucked up.
你的资料匣塞爆啦，老兄！
Your information tray is jammed, man.
你知道十二猴子军是什么吗？
Do you know what it is, the Army of the Twelve Monkeys?
一群想拯救雨林的疯狂滥好人
It's a collection of space- case do- gooders saving rain forests.
我跟那些笨瓜一点关系也没有
I have nothing to do with those bozos.
我才不要当那些 没用狂热人士的摇钱树！
I quit being the rich kid fall guy... for a bunch of ineffective fanatics.
都是你的大计划啦，混帐！
So much for your grand plot, asshole.
父亲多年来一直在警告大家
Father's been warning people about dangers of...
DNA病毒实验的危险
experimentation with D.N.A. viruses for years.
你把这资讯放进你那 昏乱失常的架构上处理过了
You've processed that information through... your addled, paranoid infrastructure.
小心啊，非营利机构
Lo and behold, a nonprofit organization...
变成阴险、革命性的阴谋
becomes some sinister, revolutionary cabal.
这人完全疯了！
This man is complete bat shit.
各位先生女士，你们可知 他以为自己来自哪里？
Ladies and gentlemen, do you realize where he thinks... he comes from?
丹米勒队长是这次搜救行动的负责人
Capt. Dan Miller, the man in charge of the rescue operation,
他说他问过专家，专家们确定…
says he has consulted with experts, and they assure us...
要是你问我，猴子一定会吃掉 那个他妈的三明治
If you ask me, the monkey's gonna eat... that goddamn sandwich himself.
刚才是不是有人从这里跑过？
Did a man just come running through here?
…说他的主要任务是找失踪的男孩
...saying his primary... responsibility was to the missing boy.
警方说在纽斯顿州立公园 发现一具遭人勒毙的女尸
Police say that the body of a woman found... strangled in the Knutson State Park...
可能是被绑架的凯瑟琳瑞利博士
could be kidnapping victim... Dr. Kathryn Railly.
有谁看到有人从这里跑过？
Anybody see someone come through here?
…步行人士不到一小时前发现
...discovered less than an hour ago by hikers.
但我们有未经证实的报导指出
But we have an unconfirmed report...
该名二、三十岁左右的女性受害者 肢体受到严重破坏
that the victim, a woman in her late twenties or early... thirties, was savagely mutilated.
今天稍早，警方找到瑞利的弃车
Earlier in the day, police located Railly's abandoned car.
目前为止…
It was found not far...
有他的踪影吗？
Any sign of him?
没有
Nothing.
他不可能就这么消失了
He can't just disappear.
你这混蛋！
You bastard.
我很可能会死在这里！ 你这狗娘养的！
I could've died in there. You son of a bitch.
你到底在想什么？
What were you thinking of,
你这失常的混帐！
you twisted sack of shit? -  I'm sorry.
对不起，对不起我把你锁在车厢里
Sorry I locked you in the trunk.
我受够你了！
I'm sick of you.
你到哪里去了？
What have you done? Did you kill somebody?
- 你杀了人吗？ - 对 一百万，五十亿人
Yes. A million people. Five billion people.
什么？
What?
杰佛瑞戈恩说病毒是我的主意
Jeffrey Goines said it was my idea about the virus.
我们在精神病院 我被药物弄得昏昏沉沉
We were in the institution. It was... all... so fuzzy, and the drugs and all.
你认为那是我的主意吗？
Do you think it was my idea?
你想会不会是我消灭了人类？
Do you think maybe I've wiped out the human race?
没人能消灭人类
Nobody is gonna wipe out the human race.
不论是你、杰佛瑞或任何人
Not you or Jeffrey or anybody else.
都是你在脑子里乱编的，一种…
You've created something in your mind. A... Oh.
- 精神偏差？ - 一种…随便啦！
Mentally divergent? -  A... Whatever.
一种替代现实
A substitute reality...
因为你不想解决任何事
because you don't want to deal with anything.
我真希望事情是那样
I would love it if that was true.
只要你愿意，事情可以解决的 我可以帮你
It can be dealt with, but only if you want to. I can help you.
他们在追我，我们得离开这里
They're after me. We have to get outta here.
谁在追你？
Who is after you?
我想那个派对上有警察
I think there were some policemen at that party.
派对？ 你跑去参加派…
Party? You went to a par...
算了
Never mind.
你要投降而不是等他们来抓你 这点很重要
It's important you surrender... instead of their catching you running.
要是我疯了不是很棒吗？
Wouldn't it be great if I was crazy?
世界就安全了 我也不必到地下生活
The world would be okay.
- 把枪给我 - 我弄丢了
Gimme the gun. I wouldn't live underground. I lost the gun.
- 枪呢？ - 我可以在这里住
I could live right here.
这里有水、空气和星星
You got water, air, stars.
- 我要去引他们注意… - 有瓦砾
I'm gonna attract their attention... -  Debris.
…这样他们就知道我们在哪
so they know where we are.
噢，我好爱这个世界！
Oh, I love this world.
他们会叫你把手举到头顶 你要照做
They're gonna tell you to put your hands... on your head. Do what they say.
我喜欢青蛙、蜘蛛
I love the frogs, the spiders.
记住，我会跟你在一起 我会帮你，不会让他们…
Remember, I'll be with you. I'll help you. I won't let them...
然后我说要合作的事 他说他会听话，于是我…
Then I said something about cooperating, and he said he would do that.
我就上车
So, I, um... I got in the car.
谢了，然后当我…
Thanks. And when I... I started honking the horn.
我开始按喇叭，然后我下车 他就不见了
Then when I got out, he was gone. -  I'll tell you somethin'.
我告诉你吧，你是运气好
You lucked out. For a while, we thought...
我们还以为你成了南部那具 遭肢解的女尸
you were a body found downstate mutilated.
- 他不会做那种事 - 这是他攻击的人吗？
He wouldn't do that. -  This the man he attacked?
让我把话说清楚
I wanna be clear about this, okay?
这个人和另外一个当时重打我们
This man and the other one were severely beating us.
詹姆斯柯尔并没先动手 事实上是他救了我
James Cole didn't start it. In fact, he saved me.
医生，很怪耶 既然你是精神科医生
Funny thing, Doctor.
或许你可以解释给我听
Maybe you can explain it to me, you being a psychiatrist and all.
为什么遭到绑架的人
Why is it that kidnap victims always try...
总是对我们描述那个绑架他们的人？
to tell us about the guys that grabbed 'em?
而且还想要我们明白
And they try to make us understand...
那个混帐有多慈祥？
how kind these bastards really were.
在生命遭受威胁的情况下 这是正常反应
It's a normal reaction to a life- threatening situation.
他有病，懂吗？
He's sick. Okay?
他以为他来自未来
He thinks he comes from the future.
活在一个精心搭建好的幻想世界里
He's been living in... a meticulously constructed fantasy world,
那个世界即将崩解，他需要帮助
and that world is starting to disintegrate. He needs help.
好
Okay.
经过30小时的折磨 虽露疲态却显然毫发无伤
Exhausted but apparently... unharmed by her thirty- hour ordeal.
瑞利医生未发表声明 即于今早回到巴尔的摩
Dr. Railly returned to Baltimore this... morning without making a public statement.
这位作家兼精神科医生 目前隐居在家
The author and psychiatrist... is currently in seclusion at her home.
同时，警方已将脱逃的精神病人 詹姆斯柯尔所引发的一连串事件
Meantime, police have pieced together... a scenario of the series of events...
拼凑起来做出解读
that began with... escaped mental patient James Cole...
抱歉
Sorry.
不，没关系，我非常清醒，睡不着
No, it's okay. I'm just... hyperalert. I can't sleep.
要不要吃点镇静剂？
Did you take your sedative? -  I hate...
我恨那种东西，会让我头脑昏沉
those things. They mess my head up. Uh- uh.
…他开始胡作非为
...where he went on a rampage of violence.
不仅在巴尔的摩绑架了一位女性
With the kidnapping...
詹姆斯柯尔现在又残杀 亚地摩的前罪犯罗尼维根
of the Baltimore woman, James Cole... is now also wanted in connection with...
因而遭到通缉
the brutal slaying of Rodney Wiggins,
维根的尸体 在一间废弃的戏院中被发现
an ex- convict from Ardmore. His body was discovered in an abandoned theater...
就在柯尔将三位动物权益保护人士 绑缚并塞口的地点
not far from where Cole left three animal... rights activists bound and gagged...
也就是第二街上的总部附近
in their Second Avenue headquarters.
他们真的相信他会在这里出现吗？ 真是够了
Do they really believe... he's going to show up here? Please.
在加州佛雷斯诺 那片玉米田挤满了旁观民众…
And in Fresno, California, the cornfield... that was jammed with spectators...
那小男孩死了吧？
He's dead, isn't he, that little boy?
他没事，那只是他跟朋友 合搞的恶作剧
He's fine. It was just a prank he and his friends pulled.
试图将瑞克纽曼 自废弃的矿道中救出的戏剧化行动
The dramatic attempt to rescue Ricky Neuman from an abandoned mine shaft...
在玩伴们坦承 纽曼失踪不过是个恶作剧之后
ended abruptly when playmates confessed...
骤然告终
that Neuman's disappearance was a prank...
事实上，该名失踪孩童 一直躲在附近的谷仓里
and that, in fact, the missing child was hiding in a nearby barn.
我心悸动
在蓝莓坡
当我与你相遇
恭喜呀，柯尔！
Congratulations, Cole.
干得好，恭喜
Well done. Well done. -  Congratulations.
在你麻醉时所做的访谈中
During your interview, while under the influence,
你提到你喜欢音乐
you told us that you liked music.
- 这里可不是监狱 - 这是医院
-  This isn't a prison.This is a hospital.
直到你能维持平衡为止
Until you recover your equilibrium.
你还是有点晕
You're still disoriented. -  It is a stressful thing.
- 时光旅行的确很累人 - 你很禁受得起
Time travel. You stood up very well, considering.
你发现十二猴子军
You connected the Army of the Twelve
跟有名的病毒学家和他儿子有关
Monkeys with a famous virologist and his son.
剩下的让其他人接手
Others will take over now.
再过几个月就能回地面了
We'll be back on service in months.
能重回地球
We'll retake the planet.
詹姆斯，你的辛苦终于有了回报
This is it, James. What you've been working for.
完全特赦
A full pardon.
你立刻就可以出去了
-  You'll be out of here in no time.
女人会抢着追你
Women will want to know you.
我不要那些女人！ 我要好起来！
I don't want your women. I want to get well.
你会好起来的
And you will be well, James.
很快就会
Soon.
你们不存在，你们不是真的
You know, you people don't exist. You're not real.
我们不能做时光旅行
We can't travel back in time. Whoop. Whoop. Uh- uh.
你们不在这里
You're not here. You can't trick me.
你们耍不了我 你们在我脑子里
You're in my... You're in my mind.
我疯了，你们代表我的疯狂
I am insane. And you are my insanity.
他不只用了 “恶作剧”这字眼 还说那男孩是躲在谷仓里
He not only used the word 'prank,'... he said the boy was hiding in a barn.
凯瑟琳，他绑架了你耶
Kathryn, Kathryn. He kidnapped you.
你还看到他杀人
You saw him murder somebody,
你明知道他很可能也会杀了你
and you knew there was a real possibility he could kill you too.
你的情绪压力太大了
You're under tremendous emotional stress.
看在老天份上，欧文，听我说
For God's sake, Owen, listen to me.
他知道佛雷斯诺那男孩的事 还说五十亿人会死
He knew about the boy in Fresno, and he says five billion people... are gonna die.
他绝不可能知道那种事！
No way he could possibly know that.
凯瑟琳！
Kathryn.
你是个理性的人 是训练有素的精神科医生
You're a rational person. You're a trained psychiatrist.
你很清楚真实与虚假的差异
You know the difference between what's real and what's not.
大家都接受我们所说的真实 对不对？
What we say is the truth is what everybody accepts. Right?
精神病学是最新的宗教
Psychiatry... it's the latest religion.
由我们决定对与错 我们决定谁疯了、谁没疯
We decide what's right and wrong. We decide who's crazy or not.
这点很让我困扰
I'm in trouble here.
我开始失去信仰了
I'm losing my faith.
巴比，你惨啦
You sure fucked up, Bob.
但我了解
But I can understand. You don't want...
你不想被人指正错误
your mistakes pointed out to you.
老巴，这我可以理解
I can relate to that, old Bob.
嘿，我知道你在想啥
Hey, I know what you're thinkin'.
你在想我只存在在你脑中
You're thinkin' I don't exist except in your head.
我明白那个观点
I see that point of view.
但你还是能跟我说话，不是吗？
But you could still talk to me, couldn't ya?
我在1996年的真实世界看到你了
I saw you... in 1996, in the real world.
你拔掉了牙齿
You pulled out your teeth. -  Why would I pull out my teeth?
我干嘛拔掉牙齿啊？ 才不会咧
That's a no- no.
你刚才说何时见到我来着？
And when did you say you saw me?
1872年吗？
In 1872?
少烦我！
-  Leave me alone.
大吼大叫没有用
Yellin' won't get you what you want.
要动脑筋才能得到你想要的
You have to be smart to get what you want.
我想要什么？
And what do I want?
你不知道自己要什么？
You don't know what you want?
你一定知道，巴比
Sure you do, Bob.
你知道你要什么
You know what you want.
你告诉我，你说我要什么
You tell me. You tell me what I want.
要看天空和海洋
To see the sky and the ocean.
要到地球上
To be topside.
呼吸空气
Breathe the air.
跟她在一起
To be with... her.
不是吗？
Isn't that right?
那不是你要的吗？
Isn't that what you want?
巴比？
Bob?
喂？
Hello.
瑞利医生，这是费城警局的金哈帕林 抱歉这么早打电话给你
Dr. Railly, Jim Halperin, Philly P.D.
你找到他了？
Sorry to call you so early this mornin'. You found him? Is he okay?
他没事吧？
No, no.
不，医生，正好相反
Au contraire, Doctor.
你那个绑架犯朋友毫无踪迹
No sign of your good friend, the...
不过情况更棘手了
kidnapper. However, the plot does thicken.
我桌上有份弹道报告
I've got a ballistics report on my desk.
上面说你宣称 取自柯尔先生大腿的那颗子弹
It says the bullet you claim you removed...
其实是古董
from Mr. Cole's thigh is, in fact, an antique.
所有线索都证明 该子弹发射于1920年以前
And all indications are... it was fired sometime prior to the 1920s.
我过去一趟怎么样？
How 'bout I take a spin down there?
不可能
This can't be.
或许我们可以一起吃饭
Maybe you and I can grab a bite to eat.
或许你能修改或加强供词
Maybe you could revise or amplify your statement.
瑞利医生？
Dr. Railly?
不！
No.
你骗不了我们的，不行的
You can't trick us, you know.
不，长官
It wouldn't work. -  No, sir.
你不是对那将死的世界上瘾了吧？
You haven't become addicted, have you, Cole, to that dying world?
不，长官
No, sir.
我只想做好工作
I just want to do my part to get us back on top,
让我们回到地表统治
in charge of the planet.
而且我有经验，我知道有谁牵扯在内
And I have the experience. I know the people involved.
他的确是最有资格的
He really is the most qualified.
但之前那些行为
But all that behavior.
柯尔，你说我们不是真的
You said we weren't real, Cole.
我想人的头脑不适合存在于
I don't think the human mind is meant...
两种不同的…
to exist in... t- two different...
该怎么说…界域吗？
uh, whatever you called it... dimensions?
这样太累人了，你们自己也说过
It's just too stressful. You said that yourself.
很令人困惑，你不知道哪个是真的
It's very confusing. You don't know what's real and what's not.
但你现在知道哪个是真的了
But you know what's real now. -  Yes, sir. I do.
对，我知道了 不，医生，我没听过
No, no. I don't know anything about...
什么猴子军的事
a monkey army, Doctor.
没有，完全没有
No, no. Nothing whatsoever.
天啊，如果我儿子参与这种事
Good Lord, if my son was ever involved... in something like that...
很抱歉，瑞利医生 我认为跟你讨论保安问题
Yeah? Well, I'm sorry. I think it's doubly inappropriate to discuss...
实在非常不妥当
security matters with you, Doctor, uh, Railly.
但你可以放心的是
But, uh, if it will ease your mind,
不管是我儿子
rest assured that neither my son...
或是其他任何未经授权的人
nor any other unauthorized person...
都无权取得我实验室里 有潜在危险性的有机物
has access to potentially dangerous... organisms in my laboratory.
这样清楚了吗？ 谢谢你的关心
Is that clear to you now? Thank you so much for your concern.
女精神科医生！
Women psychiatrists.
我听过她的演讲
I attended a lecture of hers once.
“天眼通”
'Apocalyptic Visions.'
对，她啊
Yes. She was suddenly struck...
突然有了个有关杰佛瑞的 荒谬念头
by the most preposterous notion about Jeffrey.
她是不是也患上了她所说的
Has she succumbed to her own...
“理论性”卡桑德拉疾病啊？
'theoretical' Cassandra disease?
也许我们该检查一下保安程序
Maybe we ought to review our security procedures.
对，或许要做些改善
Yeah. Perhaps upgrade 'em, you know?
加强一点？
Beef 'em up, hmm?
再来看看我们目前掌握到的资料
Let's consider again our current information.
如果该症状首次发生于
If the symptoms were first detected... in Philadelphia...
1996年12月27日的费城 那么我们就得知…
on December 27, 1996, that makes us know that...
该疾病可能是在 1996年12月13日爆发的
It was released in Philadelphia, probably on December 13, 1996.
紧接着又发生于…
And was seen sequentially after that in...
旧金山、纽澳良
San Francisco, New Orleans.
里约热内卢
Rio de Janeiro, uh.
罗马、金夏沙
Rome, Kinshasa.
喀拉蚩、曼谷，然后是北京
Karachi, Bangkok, then Peking.
柯尔，你干得非常好
That was very well done, Cole.
有病毒吗？ 有来源吗？ 五十亿人死亡？
喂！
Hello.
里面有人吗？ 如果有，我要跟你谈谈 - 是那个绑架女人 - 喂！
Is somebody in there? If you're in there, I have to talk to you. It's the kidnap woman. -  Hello?
就是跟那个把我们绑住的人 一起来的女人
The one who was with the guy who tied us up.
关灯，快关灯！
I have to talk. Turn off the lights. Turn off the light.
- 她在干嘛？ - 她想引人注意我们，哼
What's she doin'? She's drawing attention to us, that's what.
戈恩，我不知道你现在又想搞什么
I don't know what you're up to this time,
但你会让我们惹上大麻烦
Goines, but you're gonna get us in deep shit.
对讲机准备好，电池充饱电了？
Walkies ready? Batteries charged? -  Mmm.
我看到你了！ 我看到里面有人！ 快开门
I saw you. I saw somebody in there.
他们在做秘密实验
Come on. Secret experiments. That's what they do.
秘密怪事
Secret weird stuff.
- 不只是对动物 - 我认识你
Not just on animals. -  I know you.
他们也对人做，就在…
Do 'em on people too, down at...
你有没有看到詹姆斯柯尔？ 就是那个…
-  Have you seen James Cole?
他们在观察你，在拍照
The man who... -  They're watching you. Takin' pictures. -  The police.
警察哦，我知道，你看
I know. Look.
我要跟詹姆斯连络
I have to contact James.
他来找我的时候要很小心 这点非常非常重要
It's very, very important that he's really careful when he reaches me.
你明白吗？
Do you understand that?
- 明白 - 好
Good. -  Yeah. Yeah.
詹姆斯是谁？
Who's James?
他之前跟我在一起
He was with me.
几星期前他还跟你说过话
He spoke to you... several weeks ago.
他说你们都来自未来 你在监视他
He said that you were from the future... and that you were watching him.
铁栓切割器 有没有拿到铁栓切割器？
Bolt cutters. Bolt cutters.
一打，放在面包车里
Did you get bolt cutters? -  One dozen. They're in the van.
- 对保全系统的对策想好了吗？ - 都在这，存入记忆了
Got the plans for the security system? Right here. Committed to memory. -  Hey. Hey.
嘿！ 嘿！ 你们知道她在那边干嘛吗？
You know what she's doin' out there?
- 写些什么？ - 我不知道，我又看不到
What's it say? I don't know. I can't see it.
别理我的精神科医生啦 专心做眼前的工作
Forget about my psychiatrist and concentrate on the task at hand.
你的精神科医生？
Your psychiatrist?
你刚才说是你的精神科医生？
Did you just say your psychiatrist?
前精神科医生
-  Ex- psychiatrist.
这女人当过你的精神科医生 现在她用喷漆喷我们大楼？
This woman was your psychiatrist, and... now she's spray- painting our building?
上面写什么？
What's it say?
凯瑟琳！
Kathryn.
詹姆斯？
James?
詹姆斯
James.
干嘛？ 干嘛？
James. -  What? What?
那边有警察，假装你不认识我
There's a policeman over there. Pretend you don't know me.
不，我想自首，他在哪里？
No. I want to turn myself in.
- 詹姆斯！ - 他在哪？
Where is he? Where is he? -  James. Down.
低头！ 快来
Come on.
不，没关系，我已经不疯了
No, no. It's okay. I'm not crazy anymore.
我是说我疯了，我有精神偏差
I mean, I am. I'm mentally divergent. I know that now.
我现在知道了，我要你帮我 我想要治好
I want you to help me. I want to get better.
詹姆斯！
James.
我们快走！
Let's get outta here.
他要走了
He's goin'. He's goin'.
- 我以前看过那个 - 不，你没有
I've seen that before. -  No, James, you haven't.
福特车里的人正在追她 还有其他我看不清楚的人
A guy in a Ford is chasing her and some other guy I can't see.
没关系，可能又是一次绑架
No problem. It's probably just another kidnapping...
由杰佛瑞的心理医生主演 抱歉，改成前心理医生
featuring Jeffrey's shrink. Pardon me. Make that ex- shrink.
这就是你的头子？
This is your leader?
一个大疯子告诉他的前心理医生
A certifiable lunatic... who told his former psychiatrist all his plans...
他所有的神经不负责计划？
for God knows what whacko irresponsible schemes?
天知道她在墙上写了什么
God knows what she's written on that wall.
谁管精神科医生在墙上写了什么？
Who cares what psychiatrists write on walls?
你以为我把十二猴子军的事 告诉她了？
You think I told her about... the Army of the Twelve Monkeys, huh?
不可能！
Impossible.
你知道为什么吗？ 知道吗？
Do you know why? Do you know why?
你这可怜的没用鬼
Because, you pathetically ineffectual and...
假装是动物朋友的懦夫 我告诉你为什么
pusillanimous pretend friend to animals. I'll tell you why. Because when I had...
六年前在我跟她还有牵扯的时候
anything to do with her six years ago,
还没这个计划呢，我根本还没想出来
there was no such thing, I hadn't thought of it yet.
那她怎么会知道？
Then how come she knows what's goin' on?
我的解释是
Here's my theory on that.
我还住在精神病院时
When I was institutionalized, my brain was studied...
他们假藉维护心智健康之名 仔细研究过我的脑子
inexhaustibly in the guise of mental health.
我被审讯、照X光 什么检查都做过
I was interrogated, x- rayed. I was examined thoroughly.
他们把我的一切都存进了电脑
They took everything about me and put it into a...
创造出一个我头脑的模型，对！
computer where they created a model of my mind.
他们利用那个模型产生出
Yes. Using that model, they managed to generate every thought I...
往后十年我可能会有的所有念头
could possibly have in the next ten years,
然后将之灌输到某种概率矩阵
which they then filtered through a probability matrix of some kind...
藉以判断我在那段期间内 会做的所有事情
to determine everything I was gonna do in that period.
所以你看，在我还没想出这点子以前
So you see, she knew I was gonna lead the
她就知道我将会领导十二猴子军
Army of the Twelve Monkeys into history...
创下历史
before it even occurred to me.
她比我都先知道我将会做的一切
She knows everything I'm ever gonna do... before I know it myself.
怎么样？
How's that?
卡斯基，你把这边弄好 我再跟你碰头
Kweskin, you finish here. I'll meet you there.
如果你遗漏了什么 我就剥了你的皮、把你消毒然后打烂
And if you forget one thing, I will have... you shaved, sterilized and destroyed.
- 杰佛瑞？ - 干嘛？
Jeff? -  What?
你是个伟人
You're a great man.
去他的呆瓜！
Ahh, fuck the bozos.
他真的疯了
He's seriously crazy.
你知道的
You know that.
On the lookout for...
The name is Cole.
地球宾馆
来，过去
There. Over there.
好，快点
Okay. Come on.
- 我要一间房 - 一小时35块
I need a room. -  Thirty- five bucks an hour.
一小时？
An hour?
你想算15分钟的吗？ 去别家好了
You want quarter hours? Go someplace else.
这里有
Uh, here's...
25、6、7块钱，行了吧？
twenty- five, six, seven for an hour.
嘿！ 关掉啦！
Deal? -  Hey. Turn it off.
一小时，亲亲宝贝，64号房
One hour, honey babe. Number sixty- four.
在六楼，上楼到走廊尽头
Sixth floor. Up the stairs, end of the hall.
电梯坏了
Elevator's busted.
她不是亲亲宝贝
She's not honey babe.
她是医生
She's a doctor.
我的精神科医生
My psychiatrist.
懂吗？
Understand?
老兄，只要能让你硬起来，啥都行
Whatever gets it up for you, Jack.
汤米，我是地球宾馆的查理
Tommy, this is Charlie over at the Globe.
你知道华勒斯有了个新妞吧？
You know if Wallace has a new girl?
就是新入行、有点怪的那个？
Sort of a rookie type? A little weird?
她做幻想演出吗？
Does fantasy acts?
好，你站在那边，看着月亮
Okay, you were standing there looking up at the moon.
泼着水，然后呢？
You were splashing through the water, and then what?
我想我就回到牢里了
I thought I was in prison again.
就那样？ 你回到牢里？
Just like that, you were in prison?
不，不算是
No, not really.
就跟你说的一样，都在我脑子里
Like you said. It was all in my mind.
你消失了
You disappeared.
前一分钟你还在，下一分钟就不见了
One minute you were there, the next minute you were gone.
你是不是跑进了森林，还是…
Did you run through the woods, or...
我不知道
I don't know.
不记得了
I don't remember.
竖井里的男孩事件 你怎么知道那只是恶作剧？
The boy in the well. How did you know that was just a hoax?
真的是吗？
It was?
我不知道啊
I d- didn't know.
你说他躲在谷仓里！
You said he was hiding in the barn.
我想我可能是小时候看过电视报导
I think I maybe saw a TV show about that when I was a kid,
- 有个男孩… - 不是电视报导！ 是真的！
where a boy... It wasn't a TV show. It was real.
也许这男孩看了跟我一样的电视报导 所以就学了起来
M- Maybe this boy saw the same TV show that I did, and he c- copied it.
你是对的，我精神不正常
Look, you were right. I, I am mentally ill.
我幻想出了这么多事和人
I imagined all these things, these people.
我知道他们不是真的 我可以骗过他们，我…
Ooh. -  I know they're not real. I can trick them. I, I...
我可以叫他们做我想做的事
I can make them do what I want. I worked on 'em a little bit.
我设法说服了他们 我回来这里想把病治好
I got back here to get better. -  Ah.
我可以留下
I can stay here.
你看这张照片有何感想？
-  What does this mean to you?
我好像做过一个梦…
I think I had a dream  like...
跟这个有关的
about this.
你腿上有颗一次世界大战的子弹 子弹怎么射中你的？
You had a bullet from World War I in... your leg, James. How did it get there?
我不知道，你说我会妄想
I don't know. Look, you sa... You said I had delusions.
说我创造出这个世界 你说你可以解释…
That I created this world. You said you could explain.
我不行！
I can't.
我很想，但…
I'm trying to, and...
我不敢相信我们所说、所做的一切 都已经发生过了
I, I can't believe that everything... we say or do has already happened.
我们无法改变已经发生的事
We can't change what's gonna happen.
如果五十亿人真的会死，那…
And if five billion people are gonna die, it's...
我不想知道未来
I want the future to be unknown.
我想成为健康的人
I want to become a whole person again.
我要现在成为现在
I want this to be the present.
我想留在这里，留在这个时代
I want to stay here... this time...
跟你在一起
with you.
詹姆斯
James,
你记不记得 六年前你有一个电话号码？
do you remember six years ago you had a phone number?
- 当时那号码不对 - 是个女人接的
It was the wrong number then. -  A woman answered.
在1990年那号码是错的 现在应该不会错了
It was the wrong number in 1990. It should be the right number now.
你还记得吗？
Do you remember it?
那个电话号码？ 你…
The number? Do you...
婊子，这里归我管！
This is my territory, bitch.
- 这是真的，还是我在幻想？ - 绝对是真的
Is this real, or is this one of my delusions? This is definitely real. Uh, excuse me.
抱歉，我想我们起了点误会
I, I think we've got a little misunderstanding here.
哦？
Oh?
对，我们…
Yeah. We...
哇，真的吗？
-  Gee, really?
你给我坐好！
Now, you just sit tight.
误会小姐，你给我听好
You listen to me, little Miss Understanding.
你以为可以背着我 在这一区胡作非为吗？
You think you can go around me and... peddle your ass in this part of town?
我们当然有他妈的大误会了
You bet your life we got what I would... call a major fuckin' misunderstanding.
嘿！
Hey.
詹姆斯，别这样！
James, no. Don't.
把他关进衣橱，先抢了他的钱！
Uh, put him in the closet. Take his money first.
你要我抢劫他？
You want me to rob him?
- 我们需要现金！ - 不，不！
We need cash, James. -  No, no.
叫警察！ 叫警察！
Call the cops. Call the cops.
怎么回事？
What's goin' on?
我道上有兄弟！ 别杀我
I've got friends, man. Don't fuckin' kill me. -  James. James.
詹姆斯！ 不，詹姆斯！
No, James. No.
不！ 詹姆斯！
No, James.
不！ 快开门！
No. Open the door.
你到底在干什么？
What the fuck are you doin'?
拜托别伤他，快开门
Please don't hurt him. Open the door.
詹姆斯，拜托
James, come on.
以备万一
Just in case...
万一我没疯
Just in case I'm not crazy.
他们就是这样找到我们的
This is how they find us.
用我的牙齿
By our teeth.
我再也不想被他们找到了
I don't want them to find me... ever.
我不想回去
I don't want to go back.
…本区发生案件
...calling in a domestic incident.
快出去！
-  Get out.
退后
Get back.
子弹上膛
You'd better load.
我们是警察！ 把武器丢出来 人也出来！
Police. Throw your weapons out and come on out.
嘿！
Hey.
是警察吗？
Is that the cops?
嘿，我是无辜的受害者！
Hey, I'm the innocent victim here.
我被一个吸毒的婊子
I was attacked by a coked- up whore...
和一个疯子牙医攻击
and a, a fuckin' crazy dentist.
别让人起疑
Try to blend in.
噢，天哪！
Oh, Jesus.
快走！
Come on.
这里一定有电话
There's gotta be a phone around here somewhere.
那里，在那，你看
There. O- Over there. Look.
- 我去试那个号码？ - 好
I'm gonna try that number, okay? -  Okay.
- 希望啥都不是 - 嗯
Let's hope it's nothing. -  Okay.
詹姆斯！ 詹姆斯！
James. James. It's okay.
没问题了！ 我们疯了 我们疯了，那是地毯清洁公司
We're insane. We're crazy. It's a carpet cleaning company.
地毯清洁公司？
A carpet cleaning company? -  Yeah. No superiors.
对，不是长官也不是科学家 不是未来的人
No scientists. No men from the future.
只是地毯清洁公司 他们有答录机
It's just a carpet cleaning company. They have voice mail.
你留话告诉他们想要清洁哪里的地毯
You leave a message telling... where you want your carpet cleaned.
- 你留话了？ - 对啊，我实在忍不住
You left them a message? -  Yeah. I couldn't resist.
等他们听到一个疯女人留话
Wait 'til they hear this nutty woman telling...
叫他们小心十二猴子军就好笑了
them to watch for the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
我说：“第二街上的动物解放协会…
I said, 'The Freedom for Animals Association on Second Avenue...
“就是十二猴子军的秘密基地
...is the secret headquarters... of the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.'
“他们将会做出那件事
They're the ones who are gonna do it.
“我帮不上忙了，得走了
I can't do anything more now. I have to go.
“圣诞快乐”
Have a merry Christmas.'
你不可能听得到啊
You couldn't have heard me. I...
凯瑟琳，他们接到留言了
They got your message, Kathryn.
他们播放给我听
They played it for me.
音质很差，效果不好
It was a bad recording, distorted.
我没认出你的声音
I didn't recognize your voice.
这个
和这个
For the perfect Christmas gift... -  Mmm, and this.
你没事吧？ 想要什么吗？
Is everything okay? You want anything?
女士，要我把钱 记在您的贵宾卡上吗？
Shall I put this on your account, ma'am?
不，我用现金付
No. That'll be cash.
Uh...
能不能告诉我哪一楼有卖假发？
Can you tell me what floor the wigs are on?
把那东西转成他妈的电脑
You turned the thing into a fucking computer.
- 费尔竟然相信了 - 你也知道费尔这人
And Fale believed it. -  You know Fale.
如果你们被抓了，这点我满肯定的
If you guys get nailed, which I'm pretty sure you will.
我这辈子可从来没见过你们喔！
I've never seen you before in my fuckin' life.
耶！
Aha. -  Yeah.
来吧
C'mon, c'mon.
- 推过来 - 快啊
Bring 'im through. C'mon.
好，开车！
Okay, drive.
打开袋子有什么关系？ 他眼睛被贴起来了，对吧？
What's the harm in openin' the bag? His eyes are taped, right?
对吧？
Right?
好啦
Okay. Okay.
你好啊
Hello. Hello.
生化危险物
- 想不想听听猴子说话呀？ - 好耶！
Wanna hear the monkey speak? -  Yeah.
杰佛瑞？ 我知道是你 我认得你的声音
Ahh. Jeffrey? Jeffrey, I know that's you.I recognize your voice.
不，你不认得
-  No, you don't.
我也很清楚你那变态的小计划
I also know all about your warped little plan.
你那位女精神科医生告诉我了
That lady, your psychiatrist? She told me. I didn't believe her.
当时我不相信她 因为就算是你干的也太疯狂了
It just seemed too crazy, even for you.
但为防万一，我做了些防备 好让你的计谋无法得逞
But just in case, I took steps to make... sure you couldn't go through with it.
我没有密码了，杰佛瑞
I don't have the code anymore, Jeffrey.
我没办法取出病毒
I don't have access to the virus.
我脱离了能取出病毒的那群人
I took myself...
太迟了！ 太迟了！
out of the loop. -  Too late. Too late.
老爸，我们也有对付你的计划
We've got plans for you, Dad.
Whoo, whoo, whoo, whoo. Agh. Agh. Agh.
我一直不肯相信 现在我知道是真的了，杰佛瑞？
I never let myself believe it. Now I know it's true. Jeffrey? -  Hmm?
你根本是疯了
You're completely insane.
不，我没疯
No, I'm not.
在被砍掉的老树那边有个交叉路口
There's a cross section of one... of the old trees that's been cut down.
1066年哈斯汀会战 1215年签署大宪章
1492年发现美洲大陆 1776年宣布独立
1930砍树
我生在这里
Here I was born.
死在那里
And there I died.
对你那只是短暂的一刻
It was only a moment for you.
你完全没注意
Y- You took no notice.
我看过这部电影
I think I've seen this movie before. -  Shh.
我小时候在电视上看过
When I was a kid, I saw it on TV.
别说话
-  Don't talk.
我真的看过
I did see it before.
大树…
-  Tall trees.
你来过这里？
Have you been here before?
- 是的 - 什么时候？
Yes. -  When?
你何时出生的？ 我认得这部片
I don't... recognize this. -  When were you born?
- 很久以前 - 在哪里？
Long ago. -  Where?
很重要吗？
What's the matter?
- 告诉我，媚德琳 - 不！
Tell me. Madeleine, tell me. -  No.
就跟发生在我们身上的事一样 就像过去
It's just like what's happening with us. Like the past.
电影是不会变的，它变不了
The movie never changes. It can't change.
但你每次看，每次感受都不同 因为你也变了
But every time you see it, it seems different because you're different.
你看到不一样的层面
You see different things.
请别问我
-  Please don't ask me.
如果事情已经发生而你改变不了
If you can't change anything because it's already happened,
不如闻闻花香吧
you may as well smell the flowers.
什么花？
What flowers?
那只是比方
That's an expression. -  Shh.
拜托答应我你不会再问了
Promise me you won't ask me again. Please?
凯瑟琳
Kathryn,
你为何要这么做？
why are you doing this?
我想知道，要是我错了呢？ 要是你错了呢？
I want to know why. What if I'm wrong? What if you're wrong?
要是我疯了呢？
What if I am crazy?
几周后就知道事情会不会发生
In a few weeks, it will have started or it won't.
如果到时候
If there's still...
还有足球赛、交通堵塞
football games, traffic jams, TV shows and armed robberies,
电视节目和持枪抢劫 我们会高兴得要死 见到警察还会超兴奋
we're going to be so glad that we'll be thrilled to see the police.
现在我要对你负责了
I'm responsible for you now.
中国人说如果你救了一个人的命 就要永远对那个人负责
The Chinese say once you've saved a person's life, Shh. you're responsible for it forever, so I'm committed.
你有计划吗？
Do you have a plan?
我必须知道
I have to know.
我知道得太少了
There's so little that I know.
你说你从没看过大海
You said you'd never seen the ocean.
快点，走
Hurry up. Come on.
- 杰佛瑞 - 干嘛？
Jeffrey? What?
你知道我看不到，我们在哪里？
You know I can't see.
杰佛瑞？
Where are we? Jeffrey? Please.
凯瑟琳？
Kathryn?
NORTH BY NORTHWEST- VERTlGO与 PSYCHO- 24小时希区考克电影飨宴
我们订了九点半的飞机去西礁岛
We have 9:30 reservations for Key West.
我没认出你来
I, uh... just didn't recognize you.
你看来也很不一样
Well, you look pretty different yourself.
一直是你
It was always you.
在我梦里，一直是…
In my dream. It was al...
一直是你
It was always you.
我记得你这样子
I remember you like this.
你记得？
You do?
我觉得我以前就认识你
I felt I've known you before.
我觉得老早就认识你了
I feel I've always known you.
我好怕
I'm so scared.
我们做到了
你们的飞机是几点？
What time's your flight?
- 九点半 - 可能会满赶的喔
9:30. -  Might be tight.
赶？
Tight?
不，现在时间才七点半
No. My watch says 7:30.
普通的早上是没问题，时间多得很
On your normal mornin', okay. Plenty of time.
但今天你得把十二猴子军的事 也纳入考量
But today you gotta take into account... your Army of the Twelve Monkeys factor.
什么？
What?
你刚才说什么？
What'd you say?
十二猴子啊 你们今早没听收音机吧？
Twelve Monkeys. In case you folks... didn't turn on your radio this mornin'.
一群怪人放出了动物园里的动物
Bunch of weirdos let all of the animals out of the zoo.
然后把大名鼎鼎的科学家关进了笼子
They locked up this big- shot scientist... in one of the cages.
科学家自己的儿子正是行动参与人
Scientist's own kid one of the ones did it.
动物跑得到处都是
They've got animals all over the place.
一小时前有群斑马 造成高速公路关闭
Bunch of zebras closed down the thruway 'bout an hour ago.
他们还放出了什么鸸鹋
And they got some thing called an emu.
害676公路堵塞了好几公里
It's got traffic blocked for miles on 676.
…把动物放到市区
...what they think they're accomplishing...
他们自认完成了什么呢？
by releasing an animal like this... into a city like this one. -  Oh.
他们的计划原来是这样，释放动物
That's what they were up to, freeing animals.
墙上写着“我们做到了”
On the walls. It said, 'We did it.' They meant the animals.
- 原来是指动物 - 动物，对啊
The animals, yeah.
金吉先生，请容我打个岔…
If I could interrupt for a moment, Mr. Ginger...
市政府将召开记者会
There is going to be a press conference from City Hall.
我想不会有问题的
I think it's gonna be all right.
告诉你同事，若看到这上面的人
Tell your people if they spot either one...
请不要设法抓人
of them, not to try and apprehend them.
而要通知我们 我们在机场都布好人手，由我们处理
They should notify us. We have people all... over the airport. We'll take care of 'em.
行李托运人员请到47号登机门
Skycap to gate 47, please.
…芝加哥的旅客请到17号登机门登机
...for Chicago... is now ready for boarding at gate 17.
前往明尼阿波里斯的623号班机 请到…
Flight 623 to Minneapolis is now boarding at gate...
- 我认得这地方 - 机场看起来都一样
I know this place. -  Airports all look the same.
我的梦里就是这样
This is my dream.
- 胡子掉了 - 不只在我梦里
Your mustache. It's not just my dream.
我真的到这里来了，我想起来了
I was actually here. I remember now. I... About a week or two before the...
再过一两个星期…大家会开始死亡
before everyone started dying.
小心点，他们可能在找我们
Oh. Uh, careful. They might be looking for us.
我来过这里
I was here...
- 我小时候 - 用这个
as a kid. -  Use this.
我想你当时也在
I think you were here then too. -  James.
詹姆斯！
If they identify us,
如果被认出来，我们就会被送走 那就去不了西礁岛了
they're going to send us someplace, but it won't be Key West.
- 好 - 好
Okay. -  Okay. Okay.
- 我去补胡子 - 好
I'll go fix this. -  Okay.
我去拿机票，我们在报摊会合
I'm gonna get the tickets. I'll meet you in the newspaper stand.
- 好 - 好
Okay. -  Okay.
现在广播一般讯息
This is a general information announcement.
茱蒂西蒙，我订了去西礁岛的票
Judy Simmons. I have reservations for Key West.
好
Okay. Flight 623 to Minneapolis...
前往明尼阿波里斯的623号班机 请到44号登机门
is now boarding at gate 44.
我可没看过这么多现金
I don't see a lot of this. It's cash.
一言难尽
-  It's a long story.
大约20分钟后开始登机
We'll begin boarding in about 20 minutes.
- 西蒙小姐，祝你旅途愉快 - 谢谢
You have a nice flight, Miss Simmons.
Thank you.
嗨，你好吗？
Hello. How are you today?
我不知道你们在不在
I don't know whether you're there or not.
或许你们只是清洁地毯
Maybe you just clean carpets.
如果是这样，那你们很幸运 会有一段又久又快乐的人生
If you do, you're lucky. You're gonna live a long, happy life.
但如果另一个你们在听 如果你们听到这个讯息
But if you other guys are out there, if you're picking this up,
别管十二猴子军了
forget about the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
不是他们干的，那是误会 是别人干的
They didn't do it. It was a mistake. Someone else did it.
十二猴子军 只是一群爱搞怪的傻孩子
The Army of the Twelve Monkeys is just a... bunch of dumb kids playin' revolutionaries.
听好
Listen.
我的任务完成了 我做了你们要我做的事
I've done my job. I did what you wanted.
祝好运，我不回去了
Good luck. I'm not coming back.
旧金山、纽澳良
Whoo- ee. San Francisco, New Orleans.
里约热内卢、罗马
Rio de Janeiro, Rome.
金夏沙、喀拉蚩、曼谷和北京
Kinshasa, Karachi, Bangkok and Peking.
先生，您这趟旅途可远啦 要在一周内去这么多地方？
This is some trip you're taking, sir. Is this all in one week?
业务需要
Business. -  Hmm.
旅途愉快
Have a good one, sir.
无人看管的行李将被移走并损毁
Any luggage found unattended will be removed and destroyed.
巴比，有问题吗？
Got yourself a prob, Bob?
别管我！
Leave me alone.
我报告过了，我不必那么做的
I made a report. I didn't have to do that.
重要的是
Point of fact.
你不属于这里
You don't belong here.
你不准留下来
It's not permitted to let you stay.
这才是现代
This is the present.
这不是过去，也不是未来
This is not the past. This is not the future.
这是现在！
This is right now. I'm not leaving'. Get that?
我才不走，懂吗？ 你不能阻止我
You can't stop me.
随你怎么说，大哥，不关我的事
Anything you say, Chief. It's none of my business.
搭乘班机…
Passengers for flight...
柯尔
Hey, Cole.
别管我！ 别管我！
-  Leave me alone.
冷静点，柯尔，是我啊
Calm down, Cole. It's me. Cole, it's me.
荷西？
Jose?
对，荷西
-  Yeah, right. Jose.
你干嘛把牙齿拔掉？ 真神经
Why'd you pull out the tooth? That was nuts.
- 来，拿去 - 这是什么？
Here, take this. -  What? What for? Are you crazy?
- 干嘛？ 你疯了吗？ - 我？ 你开啥玩笑？ 你才疯了吧
Me? Are you kidding? You're the one. You're a hero, man.
你是英雄耶，他们给你特赦了
They gave you a pardon. What do you do?
结果呢？ 你跑回来拔掉牙齿
You come back and fuck with your teeth.
你怎么找到我的？
How did you find me?
电话啊，那通电话
-  The phone call, man.
他们把讯息还原了
They did their reconstruction thing on it.
电话？
The phone? The phone call I just made?
我刚才打的那通电话？ 五分钟前？
Five minutes ago. -  Yeah, five minutes ago.
对，五分钟前、三十年前 他们把讯息还原了
Thirty years ago. They just put it together.
“我是柯尔詹姆斯 不知道你们在不在
'Uh, hey, this is Cole, James. I don't know whether you're there...
“也许你们只是清洁地毯的” 你怎么想得出这种话啊？
or not. Maybe you just clean carpets.' Where'd you get that from? 'Forget...
“别管十二猴子军了”
about the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.'
天啊，要是他们 早点听到这消息就好了
Man, if only they could've got your message earlier.
拿去吧，只要你合作 还是可以当英雄
Take it. You could still be a hero if you cooperate.
来啊，詹姆斯，没关系
Come on, James. It's okay.
发现科学家被锁在大猩猩笼子里
- 这是找你的钱，谢谢 - 谢谢
Here's your change. Thank you. -  Thank you.
- 抱歉 - 没关系
Sorry. -  No problem.
- 嗨 - 嗨
Hi. -  Hi.
前往旧金山的784班机 在38号登机门准备登机
Flight 784 for San Francisco is ready for boarding at gate 38.
Flight 784 for San Francisco is ready for boarding...
诺贝尔奖得主戈恩
噢，天哪！
Oh, my God.
我要听命行事
I got orders. You know what I'm supposed...
你知道如果你不听话 他们要我做什么吗？ 射杀那女人
to do if you don't go along? Shoot the lady.
- 什么？ - 你懂了吧？
What? You got that?
他们说：“若柯尔不听…”
They said, 'If Cole don't obey...'
我就打烂你他妈的…听到没？
I'll break your fuckin'... You hear me?
志愿者请到37号登机口登机
Volunteers now boarding at gate 37.
看到没？ 我别无选择
You see? I had no choice.
我接到的命令就是这样，拿去吧
These are my orders, man. Just take it.
快拿去
Take it.
这部份跟病毒根本无关，对吧？
This part isn't about the virus at all, is it?
只是要听命行事而已
It's about followin' orders.
做他们叫你做的事
About doin' what you're told.
你拿到特赦了，还想怎样？
Hey, man. You got a pardon. What do you want?
我要对谁开枪？ 我要对谁开枪？
Who am I supposed to shoot? Who am I supposed to shoot?
詹姆斯！ 是戈恩的助手 他是号称有天眼通的疯子
James. James. Dr. Goines's assistant. He's an...
我想他有涉案
apocalypse nut. I think he's involved.
下一班前往旧金山的班机 将从38号登机口起飞
The next flight to San Francisco leaves from gate 38.
如果他在，那我确定他有涉案
If he's there, I'm sure he's part of it.
…请到13号登机口
...please go to gate 13.
荷兹先生，要不要过来看看？
Mr. Holtz, you wanna have a look at this, please?
抱歉，先生
Excuse me, sir. Would you mind...
能否让我看看你皮箱子里的东西？
letting me have a look at the contents of your bag?
- 我吗？ - 我们没时间了
Me? We don't have time for this.
借过！
Excuse me.
是生物标本
Biological samples.
这是证明文件
I have the papers right here. -  Yeah.
我想请你打开来
I'm gonna have to ask you to open this up, sir.
打开？
Open it?
当然没问题
Why, yes, of course.
还有什么更好？ 看这边 快点，看飞机
What could be better? Look over here. Look at the planes. Hurry up.
- 借过 - 女士，你要排队
Excuse me. Ma'am, you have to get in the line.
看吧？
See?
生物样品，文件上有写
Biological. Check the papers.
一切正常，我有许可证的
It's all proper. I have a permit.
是空的
It's empty. -  Well, yes, to be sure.
当然，看起来是空的 但我向你保证并不是
It looks empty; but I assure you, it's not.
- 你不懂 - 不，你才不懂
You don't understand.
你要排队
No, I don't have to understand. You have to get in line.
那个人带有致命病毒！
This is very important. There's a man. He's carrying a deadly virus.
在那边
There, you see?
用肉眼是看不见的
Also invisible to the naked eye.
甚至连
It doesn't...
气味都没有
even have an odor.
我不需要闻
That's not necessary, sir. There you go.
好了，感谢你的合作 祝旅途愉快
Thank you for your cooperation. Have a good flight.
好
Yeah.
- 你说谁低能？ - 我说你是他妈的低能！
Who are you calling a moron? -  I am calling you a fucking moron.
- 他妈的低能？ - 别碰她
Fucking moron? -  Get your hands off her.
等一等，等一下
Hold it. Wait a moment.
他妈的低能？ 我不准你过
Fuckin' moron? You're not gettin' through.
给我排队
Now get in the line.
我说别动！
I said stop.
他在那里！ 那个人！ 他怀有致命病毒！
There he is. That man. He's carrying a deadly virus.
阻止他！ 快来人阻止他！
Stop him. Somebody, please stop him.
我是警…
Police Offi...
他有枪！
He's got a gun.
小心！
Watch it.
不！
No.
别动！
Freeze.
借过
Excuse me.
讨厌死了
It's obscene,
一堆暴力、疯子
all the violence, all the lunacy.
竟然在机场开枪
Shootings even at airports now.
简直可说 我们是下一个濒临绝种的生物了
You might say that we're the next endangered species.
人类啊
Human beings.
你说得没错，女士
I think you're right, ma'am.
你说得再正确不过了
I think you've hit the nail on the head.
我叫琼丝
Jones is my name.
做保险的
I'm in insurance.
我看到绿树
还有红玫瑰
我看过花朵绽放
只为你和我
而我暗想
这世界真美好
我看见蓝天
还有白云
明亮幸福的白天
黑暗吓人的夜晚
而我暗想
这世界真美好
七彩的彩虹
在天空多么美丽
同时也映照在
行人脸上
我看见朋友在握手
问对方好不好
他们真的在说我爱你
我听见婴儿哭泣
看着他们成长
他们会学到的事
比我所知还多
而我暗想
这世界真美好
对，我暗想
噢，对